<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Plus-F</title>
    <link>http://replace-this-with-your-hugo-site.com/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Plus-F</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 30 May 2016 11:47:26 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://replace-this-with-your-hugo-site.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Version 0.5</title>
      <link>http://replace-this-with-your-hugo-site.com/release-notes/0.5/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 May 2016 11:47:26 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://replace-this-with-your-hugo-site.com/release-notes/0.5/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Initial public release&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Emulation is still rather buggy (I will add fixes, but for the moment consider it the equivalent of a wobbly RAM pack
or tape loading errors!)

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reset doesn&amp;rsquo;t always work properly&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some snapshots fail to load if the Emulator has been running for some time&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>http://replace-this-with-your-hugo-site.com/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 May 2016 22:31:58 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://replace-this-with-your-hugo-site.com/about/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Do you remember Match Day II?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Long before FIFA, Pro Evolution Soccer or any of the others, Match Day II managed to succinctly capture the essence of
football in just 48k. No fouls, free kicks, substitutions, sendings-off or penalties - just pass, tackle, volley, head
and save. You can easily imagine how a well-worked goal in Match Day II must look much like a football purist&amp;rsquo;s idea of
perfection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, none of this was in the minds of me or my friends when we were growing up playing this Match Day II. All we
had was this compellingly playable game, and a conviction that we must be the best people in the world at playing it.
Time passes, people move on and circumstances change, but from time to time I couldn&amp;rsquo;t help but wonder if my friends
and I were to play Match Day II against each other once more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only surprise is that it took me so long to come up with the idea of Plus-F as a way of answering that question.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Connect</title>
      <link>http://replace-this-with-your-hugo-site.com/connect/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 May 2016 22:31:58 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://replace-this-with-your-hugo-site.com/connect/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Playing in two-player mode works by one player running the Plus-F Emulator, and the other one running the Guest.
The player running the Emulator has full control of the keyboard, and sends a copy of the screen to the Guest at
a rate of 25 times a second. Meanwhile, keypresses on the Guest are translated into Kempston joystick movements and
sent back to the Emulator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;who-should-run-the-emulator:94545177397886f3162838504e334017&#34;&gt;Who should run the Emulator?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Generally, because the Emulator has to send much more data to the Guest than the Guest does back to the Emulator, the
player with the better network upload speeds should run the Emulator. If both players are connected to the same
router, it probably doesn&amp;rsquo;t matter which is which, but over the Internet this does become significant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;firewalls-and-network-connectivity:94545177397886f3162838504e334017&#34;&gt;Firewalls and network connectivity&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to keep network play as responsive as possible, Plus-F uses direct communication between the Emulator and
the Guest (commonly known as Peer-to-Peer or P2P communication). Depending on your computer and internet service
provider&amp;rsquo;s security settings, you may need to change some firewall rules so that the Emulator and Guest can reach
each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Details of how to do this will vary based on the operating system, router and ISP you are using, but you need to ensure
that your computer can receive inbound UDP network traffic on ports 7000 and 7001. If you&amp;rsquo;re already familiar with
enabling multi-player games on your computer, the process you need to follow for Plus-F will be similar to that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;making-a-connection:94545177397886f3162838504e334017&#34;&gt;Making a connection&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, the two players need to tell each other how the Emulator and Computer can reach one another. Each player should
invoke the &lt;em&gt;Get connection details&lt;/em&gt; item from the &lt;em&gt;Network&lt;/em&gt; menu, and send the host and port details displayed to the
other player.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other player then invokes the &lt;em&gt;Connect to guest/emulator&lt;/em&gt; item from the same menu to make the connection.
Eventually, the Emulator&amp;rsquo;s display should be sent to the Guest, and status messages below the display on both the
Emulator and the Guest will indicate the status and quality of the connection.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Download</title>
      <link>http://replace-this-with-your-hugo-site.com/download/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 May 2016 22:31:58 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://replace-this-with-your-hugo-site.com/download/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;download-java-first:147ca6d03f222fe2ead83908bb3bcedf&#34;&gt;Download Java first&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Plus-F requires a recent version of Java 8 in order to run. You can download this for free from
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.java.com&#34;&gt;www.java.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;download-plus-f:147ca6d03f222fe2ead83908bb3bcedf&#34;&gt;Download Plus-F&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Emulator and the Guest are bundled together as a single package. Once the download completes, unzip it
somewhere on your computer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://download.socialthingy.com/plus-f.zip&#34;&gt;Click here to download the latest version of Plus-F&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The package contains an image of the 48k ZX Spectrum ROM, which is required in order for the Emulator to
operate. This ROM remains copyright of Amstrad, and Amstrad have kindly given their permission for the
redistribution of their copyrighted material but retain that copyright.
(Full details &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/forum/#!msg/comp.sys.amstrad.8bit/HtpBU2Bzv_U/HhNDSU3MksAJ&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;release-notes:147ca6d03f222fe2ead83908bb3bcedf&#34;&gt;Release Notes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can read the release notes for the Emulator and Guest &lt;a href=&#34;http://replace-this-with-your-hugo-site.com/release-notes&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;licensing:147ca6d03f222fe2ead83908bb3bcedf&#34;&gt;Licensing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both the Emulator and the Guest are distributed under an MIT license:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MIT License&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Copyright &amp;copy; 2016 Alan Gibson&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Permission is hereby granted, free of charge, to any person obtaining a copy
of this software and associated documentation files (the &amp;ldquo;Software&amp;rdquo;), to deal
in the Software without restriction, including without limitation the rights
to use, copy, modify, merge, publish, distribute, sublicense, and/or sell
copies of the Software, and to permit persons to whom the Software is
furnished to do so, subject to the following conditions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The above copyright notice and this permission notice shall be included in all
copies or substantial portions of the Software.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;THE SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED &amp;ldquo;AS IS&amp;rdquo;, WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, EXPRESS OR
IMPLIED, INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO THE WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY,
FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE AND NONINFRINGEMENT. IN NO EVENT SHALL THE
AUTHORS OR COPYRIGHT HOLDERS BE LIABLE FOR ANY CLAIM, DAMAGES OR OTHER
LIABILITY, WHETHER IN AN ACTION OF CONTRACT, TORT OR OTHERWISE, ARISING FROM,
OUT OF OR IN CONNECTION WITH THE SOFTWARE OR THE USE OR OTHER DEALINGS IN THE
SOFTWARE.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Games</title>
      <link>http://replace-this-with-your-hugo-site.com/games/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 May 2016 22:31:58 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://replace-this-with-your-hugo-site.com/games/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Spectrum games are available for use in emulators in a number of file formats, the most popular ones being
Z80, TAP and TZX. At present, Plus-F can only load and run Spectrum programs distributed as Z80 files. Further, it
can only run 48k programs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t forget that the classic Spectrum games we can play today on emulators remain the result of the skills and
dedication of the programmers who developed them. While many have granted free distribution rights for their games,
others have not, and it is their right to do so. As such, please be considerate when downloading emulator files,
and refer to the information &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.worldofspectrum.org/permits&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.worldofspectrum.org/permits/publishers.html&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.worldofspectrum.org/permits/individuals.html&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;
for full details on which publishers and developers have granted free distribution rights.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Emulator</title>
      <link>http://replace-this-with-your-hugo-site.com/emulator/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 May 2016 22:31:58 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://replace-this-with-your-hugo-site.com/emulator/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;The Plus-F Emulator is a program that emulates a ZX Spectrum, with the following features and limitations:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Emulates a 48k Spectrum, and not a 128k variant (e.g. 128, +2 or +3)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Supports loading of Z80 snapshot files&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No sound support&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Emulation timing is not 100% accurate with respect to a &amp;ldquo;real&amp;rdquo; Spectrum&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;so-where-is-the-symbol-shift-key:11cce0584e53f34ef8f2f9d832f5cf58&#34;&gt;So where is the symbol shift key?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The CTRL key is used in place of the Spectrum&amp;rsquo;s symbol shift key.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-to-use-it:11cce0584e53f34ef8f2f9d832f5cf58&#34;&gt;How to use it&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Emulator is controlled by the options in the menu bar at the top of the screen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;file-menu:11cce0584e53f34ef8f2f9d832f5cf58&#34;&gt;File menu&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Load: Load a Z80 snapshot file&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Quit: Quit the Emulator&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;computer-menu:11cce0584e53f34ef8f2f9d832f5cf58&#34;&gt;Computer menu&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reset: Reset the Emulator (just like pulling the plug out and putting it back in again)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fast mode: Run the Emulator faster than a real Spectrum&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;network-menu:11cce0584e53f34ef8f2f9d832f5cf58&#34;&gt;Network menu&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get contact info: Display the contact information you need to give to the Guest for a two-player gaming session.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Connect to guest: Enter the contact information of a Guest for a two-player gaming session.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Disconnect from guest: Disconnect from a Guest to stop a two-player gaming session.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Guest</title>
      <link>http://replace-this-with-your-hugo-site.com/guest/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 May 2016 22:31:58 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://replace-this-with-your-hugo-site.com/guest/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;The Plus-F Guest is a program that receives screen updates from a Plus-F Emulator across a network, and sends back
keypresses translated to Kempston joystick movements. This means that a user of the guest can participate in a
two-player game, provided the game has Kempston joystick support (most have).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;keyboard-controls:d7fc600d3e074e81e78248f47945b74b&#34;&gt;Keyboard Controls&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At present, controls are not redefinable and are fixed to the conventional ones below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Q: Up&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A: Down&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;O: Left&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;P: Right&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;M: Fire&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;menu-items:d7fc600d3e074e81e78248f47945b74b&#34;&gt;Menu items&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Guest can also be controlled by the options in the menu bar at the top of the screen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;file-menu:d7fc600d3e074e81e78248f47945b74b&#34;&gt;File menu&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Quit: Quit the Guest&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;network-menu:d7fc600d3e074e81e78248f47945b74b&#34;&gt;Network menu&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get contact info: Display the contact information you need to give to the Emulator for a two-player gaming session.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Connect to emulator: Enter the contact information of an Emulator for a two-player gaming session.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Disconnect from emulator: Disconnect from an Emulator to stop a two-player gaming session.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>