<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Plus-F</title>
    <link>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/tags/software-development/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content on Plus-F</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    <atom:link href="http://plusf.socialthingy.com/tags/software-development/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>If You Only Do One Thing</title>
      <link>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/blog/if-you-only-do-one-thing/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Nov 2016 23:25:34 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/blog/if-you-only-do-one-thing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Over the years, there have been all number of innovations, techniques, tools,
tricks and fads purported to help you build better-quality applications more quickly - model-driven code generation,
object-relational frameworks, IoC containers, unit testing, Scrum, Kanban, documenting everything, documenting nothing,
pair programming - even industrial quantities of XML (in the case of the abomination that was SOAP). For me, though,
one stands head and shoulders above all the rest, Test-Driven Development. If you only do one thing tomorrow that you
aren&amp;rsquo;t doing today, choose TDD.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I came to the TDD party pretty late. Of course, I&amp;rsquo;d known all about unit testing for a long time, but
I&amp;rsquo;d never actually seen it work, in terms of improving the speed or quality of application development. What I&amp;rsquo;d
generally seen was that a conscientious newcomer to some team would write tests for new code they were working on, plus
maybe a few other tests where they had to fix existing code. Those tests would be maintained for a period of time,
before falling into (for want of a better word) disrepair, spending as much time failing as passing, and eventually
being deleted or ignored. When I first came into a TDD environment, it opened my eyes to how to make proper use of
automated tests, and when I look back at the times before I used TDD, I see nothing but missed opportunities to build
better software.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve done TDD with JUnit, ScalaTest, PyTest, Nose and Cucumber, and it works well with any and all of them. I don&amp;rsquo;t
think the choice of tools is especially important - just pick the ones that work for you and use them. Even if you&amp;rsquo;re
still writing programs in COBOL for mainframes, I&amp;rsquo;m sure there are options out there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t think I would have attempted Plus-F if I wasn&amp;rsquo;t already doing TDD in my day job. A processor is basically a
large collection of instructions which all operate on the same global state. Those instructions can then be combined in
an infinite number of permutations, where the state of a single bit in a single register can cause execution to take a
completely different path. Butterflies flap their wings at every step along the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I shuddered at the thought of having to debug a problem in some large Z80 program (i.e. Match Day II) without having
confidence that the individual processor operations were working correctly in isolation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only way to tackle it was one operation at a time, writing tests based on what the
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.z80.info/zip/z80cpu_um.pdf&#34;&gt;Z80 User Manual&lt;/a&gt; specified, writing the code for the operation, then moving on
to the next. Dull, yes, but it&amp;rsquo;s the only way I could see of gaining any traction. As it is, having taken the TDD
approach, the major problems which stopped programs from working outright have been reasonably rare, obvious and easy to
debug and fix.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By now, you may have read about my &lt;a href=&#34;../fundamentals&#34;&gt;valiant but doomed attempt to write Plus-F in Python&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;ll confess that
the thought of having to start again from scratch did make me think twice about what I was doing, but the choice was made
easier by the one thing I had in my favour - a good set of tests for all of the processor emulation. And, given that I
hadn&amp;rsquo;t got much beyond that part (aside from a prototype display that showed just how slow the emulator was), that meant
I had a good set of tests for more or less everything that I needed to rewrite. Admittedly, those tests were in Python&amp;rsquo;s
&lt;a href=&#34;https://nose.readthedocs.io/en/latest/&#34;&gt;Nose framework&lt;/a&gt;, but picking up on something else I&amp;rsquo;d learned over the previous
year or two, a typical test looked like this one:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;def test_and_a_with_other_reg_giving_zero_result(self):
    # given
    self.given_register_contains_value(&#39;a&#39;, 0b10101010)
    self.given_register_contains_value(&#39;b&#39;, 0b01010101)

    self.given_next_instruction_is(0xa0)

    # when
    self.processor.execute()

    # then
    self.assert_register(&#39;a&#39;).equals(0b00000000)
    self.assert_register(&#39;b&#39;).equals(0b01010101)

    self.assert_flag(&#39;s&#39;).is_reset()
    self.assert_flag(&#39;z&#39;).is_set()
    self.assert_flag(&#39;h&#39;).is_set()
    self.assert_flag(&#39;p&#39;).is_set()
    self.assert_flag(&#39;n&#39;).is_reset()
    self.assert_flag(&#39;c&#39;).is_reset()
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words, it read sort of like a mini-DSL. A bit of judicious search-and-replace meant that I could port tests
like these easily to an equivalent in ScalaTest like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-scala&#34;&gt;&amp;quot;and &amp;lt;reg&amp;gt;&amp;quot; should &amp;quot;calculate a zero result when a and &amp;lt;reg&amp;gt; have no shared bits&amp;quot; in new Machine {
  // given
  registerContainsValue(&amp;quot;a&amp;quot;, binary(&amp;quot;10101010&amp;quot;))
  registerContainsValue(&amp;quot;b&amp;quot;, binary(&amp;quot;01010101&amp;quot;))

  nextInstructionIs(0xa0)

  // when
  processor.execute()

  // then
  registerValue(&amp;quot;a&amp;quot;) shouldBe binary(&amp;quot;00000000&amp;quot;)
  registerValue(&amp;quot;b&amp;quot;) shouldBe binary(&amp;quot;01010101&amp;quot;)

  flag(&amp;quot;s&amp;quot;).value shouldBe false
  flag(&amp;quot;z&amp;quot;).value shouldBe true
  flag(&amp;quot;h&amp;quot;).value shouldBe true
  flag(&amp;quot;p&amp;quot;).value shouldBe true
  flag(&amp;quot;n&amp;quot;).value shouldBe false
  flag(&amp;quot;c&amp;quot;).value shouldBe false
  flag(&amp;quot;f3&amp;quot;).value shouldBe false
  flag(&amp;quot;f5&amp;quot;).value shouldBe false
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All I then had to do was write the implementation of the DSL (easy enough), and then I had a full set of tests
available from the outset, against which I could code the Java version of Plus-F. Class-by-class, I converted
the tests and then wrote the code to pass them, and in little over a month I was back to the same point I&amp;rsquo;d reached in
Python without too much effort. Full-on TDD to the rescue!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, it would be out of character if the faint glimmer of success I saw in the distance wasn&amp;rsquo;t subsequently
extinguished by an act of stupidity, laziness, or (in this case) both.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Processor emulation isn&amp;rsquo;t the only complex thing I had to tackle when writing Plus-F. Tape loading was another
tricky area, and emulating it properly is surprisingly fiddly. There&amp;rsquo;s a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.worldofspectrum.org/TZXformat.html&#34;&gt;remarkably well-documented specification&lt;/a&gt; of the TZX emulated tape format, and in theory all that&amp;rsquo;s required is
to turn the contents of a TZX file into a stream of 0s and 1s which can be fed bit-by-bit into the emulated Spectrum.
The catch is that the timings and high/low state of the input really have to be precise, or the ROM&amp;rsquo;s tape loading
routine doesn&amp;rsquo;t work. Either the input signal won&amp;rsquo;t be recognised at all, or you&amp;rsquo;re faced with the sight of the
&lt;code&gt;R Tape Loading Error, 0:1&lt;/code&gt; error message that haunted the childhood of me and many others of my generation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Intricate and nuanced, but well-documented &amp;hellip; this is exactly the sort of thing that TDD was made for. However, by this
stage, I had a lot of Plus-F working and I&amp;rsquo;d become a bit cavalier in my attitude again. (My unfortunate dalliance with
Python was by this stage some six months in the past. How quickly the mind forgets.) Certain that I was only a few commits
away from a fully-working application, I pinned my ears back and frenziedly wrote the TZX-handling routines, supported by
only a smattering of tests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Surprisingly, the code worked. Sadly, however, it was laughably inefficient. When reading from a TZX file, the screen
refresh rate would slow noticeably, and I&amp;rsquo;m sure all the lights in the house became dimmer while it was running too. It&amp;rsquo;s
hardly unheard of first implementations to be lacking performance-wise, so I could treat it as a proof of concept and
rewrite it piece-by-piece so that it skipped along more efficiently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s where the problems &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; began. Inefficient as it may have been, the first TZX routine was fairly good functionally.
But because I didn&amp;rsquo;t have a thorough set of tests which allowed me to make changes and still verify that each part worked,
any time I did something that made it run faster, I also introduced a bug somewhere else. In a bid to stop the incessant
cycle of fixing one bug only to introduce another, I resorted to cobbling together a &amp;ldquo;regression test&amp;rdquo; based
on &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/alangibson27/plus-f/blob/master/plus-f/src/test/java/com/socialthingy/plusf/tape/ReferenceVariableSpeedBlock.java&#34;&gt;this class from the original, inefficient, implementation&lt;/a&gt;
and testing all of my potential improvements with respect to that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It helped, but was nothing more than a length of wallpaper to cover up the cracks in my approach. It&amp;rsquo;s still there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thankfully, I haven&amp;rsquo;t had to touch the TZX-handling routines much of late, but I dread the day that I have to. I think
it&amp;rsquo;s pretty clear to see, when comparing &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/alangibson27/plus-f/tree/master/plus-f/src/main/java/com/socialthingy/plusf/tape&#34;&gt;its code&lt;/a&gt;
with the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/alangibson27/plus-f/tree/master/plus-f/src/main/java/com/socialthingy/plusf/z80&#34;&gt;Z80 emulation code that was developed with a TDD approach&lt;/a&gt;,
that not building it by TDD has caused a lot of problems there needn&amp;rsquo;t have been.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lesson? It&amp;rsquo;s all too easy to consider brushing TDD aside in an effort to get to where you want to be more quickly,
but no matter how much you try to rationalise it, it&amp;rsquo;s still just cutting corners. You can&amp;rsquo;t just wave away the inherent
complexity of software when it suits, but you can certainly use TDD to tame it a bit.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Fundamentals are Important</title>
      <link>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/blog/fundamentals/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Nov 2016 22:43:30 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/blog/fundamentals/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The relationship between a programmer and a language is much like the relationship between the cricketer and a
bat. Unless you know how to handle it properly, you&amp;rsquo;re not going to achieve much and you could end up in a lot of pain.
And so it was with +F, or at least the program which eventually became +F. It started off with the working title
&lt;em&gt;QAOPM&lt;/em&gt;, and was written in Python.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The choice of language was driven by a couple of things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, I aimed to write a cross-platform emulator. Python is readily available on both of my target platforms (Linux and
Windows), and I planned to use the Pygame library to build the user interface. Second, I love Python&amp;rsquo;s
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.python.org/dev/peps/pep-0020/&#34;&gt;principles&lt;/a&gt;, its elegance and its clarity. (I know the fact that whitespace
is syntactically relevant bothers some people, but it looks natural to me, and it&amp;rsquo;s never tripped me up.) My
opportunities to work with this language had been limited to a few utilities and the odd simple web application,
and I relished the chance to learn more on a project that was a bit more meaty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That decision made, I set about writing +F, and four enjoyable months later (well, as enjoyable as jumping armpits-deep
into the Z80 reference manual can be) I had a basic working version which could load a program from a snapshot file,
emulate the Z80 and render the Spectrum display. It couldn&amp;rsquo;t accept keyboard input so you couldn&amp;rsquo;t actually do much with
it, but I was sure that would follow in short order. All the unit tests worked, the display rendering was accurate,
and it was time to fire it all up together for the first time and give it a shakedown.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And &amp;hellip; it was slow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not a little sluggish, not jerky from time to time, but truly, painfully slow. Right from the outset, I&amp;rsquo;d been sure
that a modern PC (even my 2010-vintage laptop) would be able to handle emulation of an 8-bit computer without breaking
sweat. After all, there&amp;rsquo;s already an &lt;a href=&#34;http://torinak.com/qaop&#34;&gt;emulator written in JavaScript&lt;/a&gt; that runs at full speed
in a browser, so while I was expecting I&amp;rsquo;d need to make a few tweaks here and there, I had just assumed that the emulator
would be fast enough. Not so. What was the problem?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not Python. Definitely not Python.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(At this point, I want to make perfectly clear that I&amp;rsquo;m certain that in the hands of an experienced Python programmer,
it is possible to write an emulator with the requisite speed to be usable. If that sounds like you, I&amp;rsquo;ve left all of
the code for the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/alangibson27/qaopm&#34;&gt;Python +F on GitHub&lt;/a&gt;, and in the interests of learning how to
become a better programmer, I&amp;rsquo;d be very happy if you had the time to take a look and could explain to me how I could
have achieved a better outcome. I&amp;rsquo;m not having a bash at Python, I&amp;rsquo;m having a bash at me.)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve earned a living for almost two decades writing software in Java, and more recently Scala. I&amp;rsquo;ve become to an
extent conditioned to think of software solutions in terms of interactions between objects (although obviously Scala
opens the door to a more functional approach too), and that&amp;rsquo;s how I approached the Python predecessor of +F.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The processor was a class. Each Z80 operation was a class, with related operations existing in a class hierarchy. Memory was
a class. The display was a class. Almost everything was nicely organised into classes, each with short methods which
did strictly one thing - just the way you&amp;rsquo;d unthinkingly build almost any Java application. For all
that I could read and write Python, though, I&amp;rsquo;d neglected the fact that an interpreted, dynamically-typed language
behaves differently to a compiled, statically-typed language.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out this was a really big problem for me because my code fell foul of a combination of Python&amp;rsquo;s weak spots (according to
&lt;a href=&#34;https://wiki.python.org/moin/PythonSpeed/PerformanceTips#Loops&#34;&gt;this page&lt;/a&gt;) - lots of field dereferencing in tight, nested for-loops.
In any other application, I may not have noticed this, but an emulator is basically just one big outer loop, which runs some
other loops inside it on each iteration. The outermost loop runs once for each display refresh cycle (50 times a second
in the case of the Spectrum), with each iteration running the processor&amp;rsquo;s fetch-execute cycle up to about 17000 times,
followed by another loop which sets the colour of each of the 49152 pixels in the display. Lots of for-loops and, in
my implementation, lots of dereferencing of fields on collaborating objects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s a representative example of how the code for a single emulated Z80 operation (&lt;code&gt;add a, (hl)&lt;/code&gt;) looked, before I
realised this there were going to be speed issues:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;class OpAddAHlIndirect(BaseOp):
    def __init__(self, processor, memory):
        BaseOp.__init__(self)
        self.processor = processor
        self.memory = memory

    def execute(self):
        value = self.memory.peek(self.processor.get_16bit_reg(&#39;hl&#39;))
        _add_a(self.processor, value, False)

    def t_states(self):
        return 7

    def __str__(self):
        return &#39;add a, (hl)&#39;

def _add_a(processor, value, carry):
    signed_a = to_signed(processor.main_registers[&#39;a&#39;])
    if carry:
        value = (value + 1) &amp;amp; 0xff
    result, half_carry, full_carry = bitwise_add(processor.main_registers[&#39;a&#39;], value)
    signed_result = to_signed(result)
    processor.main_registers[&#39;a&#39;] = result
    processor.set_condition(&#39;s&#39;, signed_result &amp;lt; 0)
    processor.set_condition(&#39;z&#39;, result == 0)
    processor.set_condition(&#39;h&#39;, half_carry)
    processor.set_condition(&#39;p&#39;, (signed_a &amp;lt; 0) != (signed_result &amp;lt; 0))
    processor.set_condition(&#39;n&#39;, False)
    processor.set_condition(&#39;c&#39;, full_carry)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The execute method is the one that is run in the emulation loop. This single method, which could in theory be executed
up to 17000 times every 1/50th of a second, was itself doing three expensive field dereferences per iteration, and when
you include those done by the &lt;code&gt;_add_a&lt;/code&gt; function it invokes, in total there are about a dozen in executing this one simple
operation!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having gone back and done the background reading I ought to have done at the start, I spent a month trying to remedy the
problem, the outcome of which was that the code for our representative &lt;code&gt;add a, (hl)&lt;/code&gt; operation became &amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;class OpAddAHlIndirect(BaseOp):
    def __init__(self, processor, memory):
        BaseOp.__init__(self)
        self.processor = processor
        self.memory = memory

    def execute(self, processor, memory, pc):
        value = memory[0xffff &amp;amp; processor.get_16bit_reg(&#39;hl&#39;)]
        _add_a(processor, value, False)
        return 7, False, pc

    def __str__(self):
        return &#39;add a, (hl)&#39;

def _add_a(processor, value, carry):
    signed_a = to_signed(processor.main_registers[&#39;a&#39;])
    if carry:
        value = (value + 1) &amp;amp; 0xff
    result, half_carry, full_carry = bitwise_add(processor.main_registers[&#39;a&#39;], value)
    signed_result = to_signed(result)
    processor.main_registers[&#39;a&#39;] = result
    set_condition = processor.set_condition
    set_condition(&#39;s&#39;, signed_result &amp;lt; 0)
    set_condition(&#39;z&#39;, result == 0)
    set_condition(&#39;h&#39;, half_carry)
    set_condition(&#39;p&#39;, (signed_a &amp;lt; 0) != (signed_result &amp;lt; 0))
    set_condition(&#39;n&#39;, False)
    set_condition(&#39;c&#39;, full_carry)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;hellip; and while reducing the number of dot-dereferences (complemented with a few other recommended techniques such as
flattening nested loops) did help a bit, it wasn&amp;rsquo;t enough to make the emulator fast enough to be viable. Suitably
discouraged, I decided to scrap the idea of writing an emulator in Python and retreated to the safer territory of Java.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where had I gone wrong?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had my cricket bat, I&amp;rsquo;d carefully seasoned it with linseed oil and I&amp;rsquo;d spent my time in the nets, honing my technique.
I&amp;rsquo;d then tried to play snooker with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hadn&amp;rsquo;t understood the fundamentals of Python. You most certainly &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; write Java-esque object-oriented programs with
it, but what is cheap in Java comes with a different cost in Python. I fell into a trap
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.joelonsoftware.com/articles/fog0000000319.html&#34;&gt;articulately described by Joel Spolsky&lt;/a&gt;, where I didn&amp;rsquo;t
see the details beneath an abstraction, and paid the price in terms of poor performance. (If you haven&amp;rsquo;t read that
article yet, stop right now, read and understand it, read it again, then read some of the other articles on Joel on Software
before coming back here. It&amp;rsquo;ll be well worth your while, trust me.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope I won&amp;rsquo;t make this particular mistake again, but how could I have avoided this problem? I could have read some
information about the performance characteristics of Python in advance of starting, of course. But given that I&amp;rsquo;m not
especially taken with the idea of lots of up-front background reading when there&amp;rsquo;s code I could be writing (this may or
may not be a character flaw, I leave that for you to judge), I think the best thing I could have done is reached a point
where I realised my mistake a lot sooner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Premature optimisation is of course a problem in itself (more on &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; later), but a spot of up-front prototyping would have
definitely helped. For example, I could have built a representative subset of the Z80 instruction set and performance
tested a few simple routines, or built the display rendering logic and tested it standalone at the required frame rate.
I&amp;rsquo;m sure that either of these would have made me either change the way I was writing my Python, or make the jump to
Java sooner than I did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In honesty, it would have been easy to give up once I realised my best chance was to start all over again, but I did
have one thing in my favour which was going to ease the pain considerably. I&amp;rsquo;ll tell you about that next time.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Seeing Clearly</title>
      <link>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/blog/seeing-clearly/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 06 Nov 2016 22:02:33 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/blog/seeing-clearly/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Before I dive into the missteps and mishaps of +F, I&amp;rsquo;d like to start with one very important thing I did right,
in the very early stages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The original idea for +F came from the tail end of an IM conversation with an old school friend, reminiscing
about the computer games we used to play when we were young. A particular favourite of ours was Match Day II
(for those of you too young to remember, it was sort of like the best bits of FIFA and PES combined in a single game,
only about a hundred times better than that) and we were at the time convinced we would be world champions at it,
if such a competition had existed. (Sadly, eSports wasn&amp;rsquo;t to come into being until a good 10 years after we were past
our gaming peak, and the world had mistakenly moved on from Match Day II by then anyway.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can&amp;rsquo;t remember who, but one or the other of us signed off by saying &lt;em&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m sure I could still hammer you&lt;/em&gt;, and
it put me to thinking &amp;hellip; which one of us would actually win? The simple way to solve it would be to get together
in front of a computer, fire up an emulator (FUSE, for example) and sort it out. Sadly, at the time, we were
on almost exactly opposite sides of the world, and it would have been a long way for either of us to fly simply
to settle an old childhood rivalry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nonetheless, it planted an idea in my mind. Given how easy it is to make high quality video calls to faraway
places, surely there must be no problem in sending Spectrum screenshots in one direction and joystick movements
in another, at least in theory? Depending on the distance and quality of network connection, things might chug
along a little slowly at times, but the Spectrum was never known as a speed machine, was it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I toyed with the idea for a while before I started any code. My first thought was whether I could bolt some
network play facilities onto an existing open-source emulator, most of which tend to be written in C or some
similar low-level language. I rejected this idea primarily because I thought trying to understand someone
else&amp;rsquo;s C code would be beyond me, but also because I wanted the emulator to be usable across Linux and
Windows, and a language with simpler cross-platform support would be a better option.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So that more or less put me in the position of writing my own emulator from the ground up. It&amp;rsquo;s a challenge I
did relish, but I wasn&amp;rsquo;t in any illusion about the amount of work it would need. Where to start?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More importantly, where to &lt;em&gt;stop&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I only wanted to be able to play a couple of games of Match Day II, so there wouldn&amp;rsquo;t be any need to go overboard
with whizzbang features that made no difference to the quality of gameplay. Those thoughts left me with a very clear
vision of what I wanted +F to be:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An emulator that worked on (at least) Linux and Windows.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Network play capability, with a fully-fledged emulator at one end and a &amp;ldquo;dumb&amp;rdquo; console at the other.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;48k model only.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Allows a full game of Match Day II to be played without crashing, even if nothing else works.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No sound.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No loading borders.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No superfluous UI features or twiddles.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And there it was, the minimum viable product for +F. I didn&amp;rsquo;t go as far as setting up a backlog for it or
anything like that, but armed with a clear idea of what I wanted, I was able to decide where to start, what to do
next, and what not to bother with. That&amp;rsquo;s really important, because even in something with a scope that seems
limited, like a Spectrum emulator, there are a lot more things going on than you might expect, and a lot of
places you could choose to put your effort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take borders. It&amp;rsquo;s possible to change the colour of the border at specific positions down the screen, and
indeed games like &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.worldofspectrum.org/infoseekid.cgi?id=0000227&#34;&gt;Aquaplane&lt;/a&gt; use this to create a
&amp;ldquo;horizon&amp;rdquo; effect that spans the full width of the screen. However, making the change at the correct position
is intimately linked with the timing of the Spectrum&amp;rsquo;s display hardware. The rules for emulating this correctly
are &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.worldofspectrum.org/faq/reference/48kreference.htm#ZXSpectrum&#34;&gt;very complicated&lt;/a&gt; and would take
an age to implement and test.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For my purposes, though, because I had already established Match Day II was my priority, and because it
doesn&amp;rsquo;t do anything at all the border (it&amp;rsquo;s black the whole time) it was an easy choice for me not to care
about this at all. This sort of focus that I had because of my clear vision of +F saved me from
disappearing off into the more arcane (but no less technically interesting) aspects of building an emulator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How does any of this relate to what you and I do in our day jobs? Well, imagine you&amp;rsquo;re maintaining a library
that&amp;rsquo;s going to be used by some other groups - maybe internal, maybe external, maybe a combination of both.
Once your code has been released into the wild for the first time, you&amp;rsquo;re bound to get people coming to you and
asking for new features. Chances are they&amp;rsquo;ll all request different things - this team wants something that
makes it easier to integrate with Spring, that team wants support for a particular metrics framework, and that
team over there wants a version that produces XML rather than JSON.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reasonable though all these requests may be, if you say &lt;em&gt;yes&lt;/em&gt; to all of them, you&amp;rsquo;ll end up with a bloated
library, it&amp;rsquo;ll be more involved to maintain and release, client teams will have a tougher time to upgrade,
and in the end every encounter with your library will become a chore rather than a pleasure. You&amp;rsquo;ll also run
the risk of losing focus on the core capabilities of your library, and you&amp;rsquo;ll spend time and effort on things
that only a fraction of your user base will use, rather than using that time to make your code more robust,
correct, efficient or easy to integrate with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end, it comes down to one thing - do you have a clear idea of what the core purpose of your library is?
Sure, you could add some code that will produce an XML form of your output, and the people who asked for it
will doubtless be thankful (today, anyway). But should your library really be getting involved in those sort of
serialisation issues - maybe it should be producing a logical model and leaving it up to the teams who use it
to decide how its output appears instead?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe adding the XML support (or whatever) &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; absolutely the right thing to do, but that&amp;rsquo;s a question only
you (and the rest of your team) can answer. If you&amp;rsquo;re given a requirement and you can&amp;rsquo;t answer the question
&lt;em&gt;Do we need this?&lt;/em&gt; with a straight &lt;em&gt;yes&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;no&lt;/em&gt;, it&amp;rsquo;s well worth your time to figure out why you can&amp;rsquo;t.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>