<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Software Development on Plus-F</title>
    <link>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/tags/software-development/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Software Development on Plus-F</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 13 Dec 2016 21:24:44 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://plusf.socialthingy.com/tags/software-development/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Going Too Quickly, Working Too Hard</title>
      <link>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/blog/optimisation/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Dec 2016 21:24:44 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/blog/optimisation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The just-about-holding-together addition of tape loading emulation I told you about
&lt;a href=&#34;../if-you-only-do-one-thing&#34;&gt;last time&lt;/a&gt; was the last but one of the major bits
of +F. Having reached this milestone, I decided to take some time out and enjoy
playing a game or two of Match Day II before doing any more work on it. My work
may have stopped, but it turns out my computer was working as hard as ever.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>If You Only Do One Thing</title>
      <link>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/blog/if-you-only-do-one-thing/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Nov 2016 23:25:34 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/blog/if-you-only-do-one-thing/</guid>
      <description>Over the years, there have been all number of innovations, techniques, tools, tricks and fads purported to help you build better-quality applications more quickly - model-driven code generation, object-relational frameworks, IoC containers, unit testing, Scrum, Kanban, documenting everything, documenting nothing, pair programming - even industrial quantities of XML (in the case of the abomination that was SOAP). For me, though, one stands head and shoulders above all the rest, Test-Driven Development.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Fundamentals are Important</title>
      <link>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/blog/fundamentals/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Nov 2016 22:43:30 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/blog/fundamentals/</guid>
      <description>The relationship between a programmer and a language is much like the relationship between the cricketer and a bat. Unless you know how to handle it properly, you&amp;rsquo;re not going to achieve much and you could end up in a lot of pain. And so it was with +F, or at least the program which eventually became +F. It started off with the working title QAOPM, and was written in Python.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Seeing Clearly</title>
      <link>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/blog/seeing-clearly/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 06 Nov 2016 22:02:33 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/blog/seeing-clearly/</guid>
      <description>Before I dive into the missteps and mishaps of +F, I&amp;rsquo;d like to start with one very important thing I did right, in the very early stages.
The original idea for +F came from the tail end of an IM conversation with an old school friend, reminiscing about the computer games we used to play when we were young. A particular favourite of ours was Match Day II (for those of you too young to remember, it was sort of like the best bits of FIFA and PES combined in a single game, only about a hundred times better than that) and we were at the time convinced we would be world champions at it, if such a competition had existed.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>