<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Plus-F</title>
    <link>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Plus-F</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 09 Mar 2019 19:06:00 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://plusf.socialthingy.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Version 2.3</title>
      <link>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/release-notes/2.3/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 Mar 2019 19:06:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/release-notes/2.3/</guid>
      <description> Support reconnection to previous peer Improved support for model detection  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Version 2.2</title>
      <link>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/release-notes/2.2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Jan 2019 19:06:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/release-notes/2.2/</guid>
      <description> Saving of snapshots in .z80 format  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Version 2.1</title>
      <link>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/release-notes/2.1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Jan 2019 19:06:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/release-notes/2.1/</guid>
      <description> Redefinable keys for joystick control  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Version 2.0</title>
      <link>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/release-notes/2.0/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Nov 2018 21:06:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/release-notes/2.0/</guid>
      <description> Revamped UI launches straight into Emulator Improved scanline timing to reduce flicker and improve rainbow effects  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Version 1.6</title>
      <link>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/release-notes/1.6/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Oct 2018 21:06:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/release-notes/1.6/</guid>
      <description> Removed use of sun.misc.Unsafe Various performance optimisations Reduced display flicker on some games  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Version 1.5</title>
      <link>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/release-notes/1.5/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Mar 2017 17:36:26 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/release-notes/1.5/</guid>
      <description> Initial (incomplete) support for 48k and AY sound.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Version 1.4.1</title>
      <link>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/release-notes/1.4.1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Feb 2017 17:36:26 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/release-notes/1.4.1/</guid>
      <description> Fix to TZX loading which allows Speedlock 2-7 to work.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Version 1.4</title>
      <link>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/release-notes/1.4/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Feb 2017 17:36:26 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/release-notes/1.4/</guid>
      <description> Support for loading TAP and TZX files inside ZIP files. Integration with World Of Spectrum archive.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Credits</title>
      <link>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/credits/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Jan 2017 20:31:58 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/credits/</guid>
      <description> The Spectrum 48k and +2 ROMs distributed with +F remain copyright of Amstrad,and Amstrad have kindly given their permission for the redistribution of their copyrighted material but retain that copyright. (Full details here.)
 The Spectrum font used on this site is ZX-Spectrum-7 by Alexander Sizenko, which he has very kindly made available as Freeware.
  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Version 1.3</title>
      <link>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/release-notes/1.3/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Jan 2017 20:27:26 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/release-notes/1.3/</guid>
      <description> Compatibility fixes for Raspberry Pi. Support logging to file.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Version 1.2</title>
      <link>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/release-notes/1.2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 18 Dec 2016 22:27:26 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/release-notes/1.2/</guid>
      <description> Added full-screen mode and rendering tweaks. Minor bugfix to tape loading.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Going Too Quickly, Working Too Hard</title>
      <link>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/blog/optimisation/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Dec 2016 21:24:44 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/blog/optimisation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The just-about-holding-together addition of tape loading emulation I told you about
&lt;a href=&#34;../if-you-only-do-one-thing&#34;&gt;last time&lt;/a&gt; was the last but one of the major bits
of +F. Having reached this milestone, I decided to take some time out and enjoy
playing a game or two of Match Day II before doing any more work on it. My work
may have stopped, but it turns out my computer was working as hard as ever.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>If You Only Do One Thing</title>
      <link>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/blog/if-you-only-do-one-thing/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Nov 2016 23:25:34 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/blog/if-you-only-do-one-thing/</guid>
      <description>Over the years, there have been all number of innovations, techniques, tools, tricks and fads purported to help you build better-quality applications more quickly - model-driven code generation, object-relational frameworks, IoC containers, unit testing, Scrum, Kanban, documenting everything, documenting nothing, pair programming - even industrial quantities of XML (in the case of the abomination that was SOAP). For me, though, one stands head and shoulders above all the rest, Test-Driven Development.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Version 1.1</title>
      <link>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/release-notes/1.1/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Nov 2016 22:27:26 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/release-notes/1.1/</guid>
      <description> Single launcher for Emulator and Guest UI tweaks Windows 64-bit Installer and Universal Zip downloads  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Fundamentals are Important</title>
      <link>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/blog/fundamentals/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Nov 2016 22:43:30 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/blog/fundamentals/</guid>
      <description>The relationship between a programmer and a language is much like the relationship between the cricketer and a bat. Unless you know how to handle it properly, you&amp;rsquo;re not going to achieve much and you could end up in a lot of pain. And so it was with +F, or at least the program which eventually became +F. It started off with the working title QAOPM, and was written in Python.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Seeing Clearly</title>
      <link>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/blog/seeing-clearly/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 06 Nov 2016 22:02:33 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/blog/seeing-clearly/</guid>
      <description>Before I dive into the missteps and mishaps of +F, I&amp;rsquo;d like to start with one very important thing I did right, in the very early stages.
The original idea for +F came from the tail end of an IM conversation with an old school friend, reminiscing about the computer games we used to play when we were young. A particular favourite of ours was Match Day II (for those of you too young to remember, it was sort of like the best bits of FIFA and PES combined in a single game, only about a hundred times better than that) and we were at the time convinced we would be world champions at it, if such a competition had existed.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Standing on the Shoulders of Giants</title>
      <link>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/blog/standing-on-the-shoulders-of-giants/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Nov 2016 20:54:07 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/blog/standing-on-the-shoulders-of-giants/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The fundamental thing an emulator does is, by definition, copy the behaviour of something else. And so it is
with +F, which emulates a real ZX Spectrum. The catch, sadly, is that I don&amp;rsquo;t have one of those to hand, so
without the real thing as a reference, how can I check that +F is working properly? The answer lies in the
fantastic emulators that others have written.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>In The Beginning</title>
      <link>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/blog/in-the-beginning/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Oct 2016 22:49:58 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/blog/in-the-beginning/</guid>
      <description>Why did I bother writing +F? There are already plenty of fully-featured, freely-available Spectrum emulators for more or less any platform you care to think of. Indeed, I remember using a perfectly playable one on the Commodore Amiga as far back as 1994 or 1995 (ZXAM by Antonio J. Pomar Roselló), so it&amp;rsquo;s hardly a novel idea.
I did have a little twist which I wanted to add, which at the time I started writing didn&amp;rsquo;t appear to be available in any other emulator, namely the ability to play games across the Internet.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Version 1.0</title>
      <link>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/release-notes/1.0/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Oct 2016 22:55:26 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/release-notes/1.0/</guid>
      <description> Performance improvements UI tweaks Revamped network connectivity  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Version 0.6</title>
      <link>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/release-notes/0.6/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Aug 2016 22:55:26 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/release-notes/0.6/</guid>
      <description> Implemented TAP and TZX support Added support for +2 Fixed some processor emulation bugs (there are still others in there)  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Version 0.5</title>
      <link>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/release-notes/0.5/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 May 2016 11:47:26 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/release-notes/0.5/</guid>
      <description> Initial public release Emulation is still rather buggy (I will add fixes, but for the moment consider it the equivalent of a wobbly RAM pack or tape loading errors!)  Reset doesn&amp;rsquo;t always work properly Some snapshots fail to load if the Emulator has been running for some time   </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Download</title>
      <link>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/download/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 May 2016 22:31:58 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/download/</guid>
      <description>Available packages  64-bit Windows Installer
 This is the simplest way to get up and running on a compatible Windows system. On Windows 10, you might see a warning from Windows SmartScreen when you run the installer. Ultimately, it&amp;rsquo;s your choice whether to trust the application you have downloaded, feel free to browse the source at https://github.com/alangibson27/plus-f if you have any qualms. To dismiss the warning, click the &amp;ldquo;More Info&amp;rdquo; text and then the &amp;ldquo;Run anyway&amp;rdquo; button.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Games</title>
      <link>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/games/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 May 2016 22:31:58 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/games/</guid>
      <description>Spectrum games are available for use in emulators in a number of file formats, the most popular ones being Z80, TAP and TZX, all of which +F can load. TAP files are at present the most reliable, although you should be able to use a lot of Z80 and TZX files as well.
One of the most authoritative sources for Spectrum games the World of Spectrum Archive, which has an extensive collection of TAP and TZX files.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Network</title>
      <link>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/network/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 May 2016 22:31:58 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/network/</guid>
      <description>How to do it Network play works by player A starting a session and player B joining:
 At least one player must to ensure that port forwarding is enabled on their router for UDP traffic, on ports 7000 and 7001. If both players can forward these ports, the chance of a successful connection is improved.
 Agree on who should start the session. Generally, the player with the better network upload speeds should do this.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Play</title>
      <link>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/play/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 May 2016 22:31:58 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/play/</guid>
      <description>+F can emulate a number of different models of Spectrum, and can load games from TAP, TZX or Z80 files. TZX files are the most authentic, TAP files are the most reliable. Only 48k Z80 snapshots are supported.
So where is the symbol shift key? The CTRL key is used in place of the Spectrum&amp;rsquo;s symbol shift key.
How to use it +F is controlled by the options in the menu bar at the top of the screen.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>