<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Plus-F</title>
    <link>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content on Plus-F</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 03 Nov 2016 21:54:07 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://plusf.socialthingy.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Standing on the Shoulders of Giants</title>
      <link>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/blog/standing-on-the-shoulders-of-giants/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Nov 2016 21:54:07 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/blog/standing-on-the-shoulders-of-giants/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The fundamental thing an emulator does is, by definition, copy the behaviour of something else. And so it is
with +F, which emulates a real ZX Spectrum. The catch, sadly, is that I don&amp;rsquo;t have one of those to hand, so
without the real thing as a reference, how can I check that +F is working properly? The answer lies in the
fantastic emulators that others have written.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I mainly run Linux at home, and over the years I&amp;rsquo;ve enjoyed using the &lt;a href=&#34;http://fuse-emulator.sourceforge.net/&#34;&gt;FUSE Emulator&lt;/a&gt;.
From my time using it, I&amp;rsquo;ve developed confidence that it is a faithful emulation of a ZX Spectrum, and at
various points in the development of +F I&amp;rsquo;ve used it as my reference. When I wasn&amp;rsquo;t sure if my Z80 emulation
code was setting flags correctly, or I wanted to see what the behaviour of a particular block of assembly code
was, I would run identical tests against FUSE and +F, and where +F gave a different answer, I could be confident
that there was a bug in there which I needed to fix.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On top of that, FUSE also comes with a handy set of debugging tools, which I also made use of at various times -
notably in checking I had the right behaviour for incrementing the value of the refresh register. (There was also
another time where I poured away days of effort trying to squash a bug I&amp;rsquo;d introduced unthinkingly as a
result of the fundamental misconception that the Spectrum ROM would never try to overwrite itself, but more
on that later.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of this is simply to say that, without FUSE, I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t have been able to develop +F. While +F does have
a few tweaks and twiddles that FUSE doesn&amp;rsquo;t have, it&amp;rsquo;s still inferior in many ways, and if you&amp;rsquo;re looking for a
solid Spectrum emulator that&amp;rsquo;s packed full of features and gives you an authentic experience, try FUSE.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also goes without saying that I&amp;rsquo;m deeply thankful to FUSE&amp;rsquo;s author for his work, and also very much in awe
of it.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why?</title>
      <link>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/blog/why/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Oct 2016 22:49:58 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/blog/why/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Why did I bother writing +F? There are already plenty of fully-featured, freely-available Spectrum emulators for
more or less any platform you care to think of. Indeed, I remember using a perfectly playable one on the Commodore
Amiga as far back as 1994 or 1995 (ZXAM by Antonio J. Pomar Roselló), so it&amp;rsquo;s hardly a novel idea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did have a little twist which I wanted to add, which at the time I started writing didn&amp;rsquo;t appear to be available
in any other emulator, namely the ability to play games across the Internet. (It turns out that &lt;a href=&#34;http://zxm.speccy.cz/realspec/&#34;&gt;RealSpec&lt;/a&gt;
claims to do this and more, but I haven&amp;rsquo;t tried it.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More than just that, though, it was probably inevitable I would end up trying this sooner or later. Much like
mountaineers are reputed to climb mountains &amp;ldquo;because they&amp;rsquo;re there&amp;rdquo;, or lovelorn teenage boys write dreadful and
embarrassing poetry, the chances of a programming geek with a fondness for 80s gaming writing an emulator are
rather high. (Given I&amp;rsquo;d already written a
&lt;a href=&#34;https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/speccy-loading-borders/jakeajfeddddpglibndhjhdmlinejihf&#34;&gt;Chrome plugin that uses CSS to emulate Spectrum loading borders&lt;/a&gt;,
it&amp;rsquo;s safe to say that I&amp;rsquo;ve got form.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;So Mr. Nerdy-Nerdy has a warm, fuzzy feeling about his pet project&lt;/em&gt;, you may be thinking. &lt;em&gt;Very good, move along.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And to a certain extent, you&amp;rsquo;re right. There&amp;rsquo;s nothing novel about +F and I certainly wasn&amp;rsquo;t planning to blog about
it. Indeed, if I was just a programming geek by night, I probably wouldn&amp;rsquo;t have, but I&amp;rsquo;ve actually also been a programming
geek by profession for the best part of two decades. When you do anything for that length of time, it becomes something
of an overlearned skill, something you don&amp;rsquo;t necessarily have to devote much conscious thought to.
You learn all manner of techniques and best practices from the people you work with, you learn your own lessons, and
most of all you tend to adopt and fit in with the way that your team works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Combine that with time pressures and shifting requirements, and it can be easy to go through the motions and forget &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt;
you do things the way you do them. Best practices which develop some form of longevity are likely to provide benefits,
but it&amp;rsquo;s easy to slip into something of a ritualistic mentality about the way you build software. &lt;em&gt;If we write the magic
number of unit tests, make sure the size in bytes of our zip file is an odd number and sacrifice a chicken, the Gods will
smile upon us and our release will be successful.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With +F being a personal hobby project, and me being answerable to nobody but myself for its success or otherwise, I
wasn&amp;rsquo;t subject to the formalities of software development which I&amp;rsquo;ve become used to in my day job. I could completely
freely choose which ones to follow and which ones to ignore. It&amp;rsquo;s fair to say that there was a fair amount of unwarranted
bravado about the choices I made, an air of &lt;em&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m old enough to know what I&amp;rsquo;m doing&lt;/em&gt; about my approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The result is the catalogue of gaffes, goofs and prat-falls you&amp;rsquo;re going to read about in this blog. I will, of course,
make the odd diversion into the simultaneously mundane and fascinating details of emulation, but what I really want to
get across as I write is that there really &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; good reasons why we do things the way we do, and if we lose sight of that
then we are bound to repeat the mistakes of the past.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That does sound rather heavy, but the flip-side is to realise that there are so many signposts guiding us down the path
to success, and it&amp;rsquo;s that note of encouragement I hope you take away with you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope you find my writing enjoyable.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Version 1.0</title>
      <link>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/release-notes/1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Oct 2016 22:55:26 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/release-notes/1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Performance improvements&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;UI tweaks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Revamped network connectivity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Version 0.6</title>
      <link>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/release-notes/0/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Aug 2016 22:55:26 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/release-notes/0/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Implemented TAP and TZX support&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Added support for +2&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fixed some processor emulation bugs (there are still others in there)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Version 0.5</title>
      <link>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/release-notes/0/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 May 2016 11:47:26 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/release-notes/0/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Initial public release&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Emulation is still rather buggy (I will add fixes, but for the moment consider it the equivalent of a wobbly RAM pack
or tape loading errors!)

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reset doesn&amp;rsquo;t always work properly&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some snapshots fail to load if the Emulator has been running for some time&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 May 2016 22:31:58 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/about/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Do you remember Match Day II?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Long before FIFA, Pro Evolution Soccer or any of the others, Match Day II managed to succinctly capture the essence of
football in just 48k. No fouls, free kicks, substitutions, sendings-off or penalties - just pass, tackle, volley, head
and save. You can easily imagine how a well-worked goal in Match Day II must look much like a football purist&amp;rsquo;s idea of
perfection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, none of this was in the minds of me or my friends when we were growing up playing this Match Day II. All we
had was this compellingly playable game, and a conviction that we must be the best people in the world at playing it.
Time passes, people move on and circumstances change, but from time to time I couldn&amp;rsquo;t help but wonder what would happen
if my friends and I were to play Match Day II against each other once more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only surprise is that it took me so long to come up with the idea of Plus-F as a way of answering that question.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Connect</title>
      <link>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/connect/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 May 2016 22:31:58 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/connect/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h3 id=&#34;how-to-do-it&#34;&gt;How to do it&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Network play works by player A running the Emulator and player B running the Guest. Both of these are downloaded and
available in the same package. Here&amp;rsquo;s how it works:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Agree on who should run the Emulator. Generally, the player with the better network upload speeds should do this.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Choose a code name and share this by email, instant message, text message or however you like.
It&amp;rsquo;s not especially important what this code is, and you can use the same one over and over again if you like.
They are only retained until the connection has been made, at which point the Plus-F Relay Service forgets it again.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Players A and B both choose the &lt;em&gt;Connect&lt;/em&gt; option from the &lt;em&gt;Network&lt;/em&gt; menu, and enter the code name in the pop-up.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;After a short while, the pop-up should disappear and the Emulator&amp;rsquo;s screen should be shared with the Guest.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The guest can use the keys Q, A, O, P and M as a Kempston joystick controller.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Status messages below the display will show the current connection status. The colour of the message indicates the
overall quality of the connection:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Green: The connection is good enough for games to be playable.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Yellow: The connection quality is poor, and delays may be experienced.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Red: The connection has dropped, either temporarily or permanently.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;does-it-really-work&#34;&gt;Does it really work?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Limited amounts of testing on the setup below have shown that it is possible for the Emulator and the Guest to be
responsive enough to one another to make two-player games playable. Clearly, some latency may occur at times, causing
the Guest&amp;rsquo;s copy of the display to jump or jerk a little.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Emulator running on Windows 10, connected to the internet wirelessly via a non-fibre connection&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Guest running on Ubuntu, connected to the internet wirelessly via a 3G phone acting as a portable hotspot
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If both Emulator and Guest are on fast wireless or wired connections, or on the same local network, performance
should be acceptable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;firewalls-and-network-connectivity&#34;&gt;Firewalls and network connectivity&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to keep network play as responsive as possible, Plus-F uses direct communication between the Emulator and
the Guest (commonly known as Peer-to-Peer or P2P communication). Depending on your computer and internet service
provider&amp;rsquo;s security settings, you may need to change some firewall rules so that the Emulator and Guest can reach
each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Details of how to do this will vary based on the operating system, router and ISP you are using, but you need to ensure
that your computer can receive inbound UDP network traffic on ports 7000 and 7001. If you&amp;rsquo;re already familiar with
enabling multi-player games on your computer, the process you need to follow for Plus-F will be similar to that.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Download</title>
      <link>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/download/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 May 2016 22:31:58 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/download/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;download-java-first&#34;&gt;Download Java first&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Plus-F requires a recent version of Java 8 in order to run. You can download this for free from
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.java.com&#34;&gt;www.java.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;download-plus-f&#34;&gt;Download Plus-F&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Emulator and the Guest are bundled together as a single package. Once the download completes, unzip it
somewhere on your computer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://download.socialthingy.com/plus-f.zip&#34;&gt;Click here to download the latest version of Plus-F&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The package contains images of the 48k and +2 Spectrum ROMs, which are required in order for the Emulator to
operate. These ROMs remain copyright of Amstrad, and Amstrad have kindly given their permission for the
redistribution of their copyrighted material but retain that copyright.
(Full details &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/forum/#!msg/comp.sys.amstrad.8bit/HtpBU2Bzv_U/HhNDSU3MksAJ&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;release-notes&#34;&gt;Release Notes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can read the release notes for the Emulator and Guest &lt;a href=&#34;http://plusf.socialthingy.com/release-notes&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;licensing&#34;&gt;Licensing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both the Emulator and the Guest are distributed under an MIT license:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MIT License&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Copyright &amp;copy; 2016 Alan Gibson&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Permission is hereby granted, free of charge, to any person obtaining a copy
of this software and associated documentation files (the &amp;ldquo;Software&amp;rdquo;), to deal
in the Software without restriction, including without limitation the rights
to use, copy, modify, merge, publish, distribute, sublicense, and/or sell
copies of the Software, and to permit persons to whom the Software is
furnished to do so, subject to the following conditions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The above copyright notice and this permission notice shall be included in all
copies or substantial portions of the Software.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;THE SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED &amp;ldquo;AS IS&amp;rdquo;, WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, EXPRESS OR
IMPLIED, INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO THE WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY,
FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE AND NONINFRINGEMENT. IN NO EVENT SHALL THE
AUTHORS OR COPYRIGHT HOLDERS BE LIABLE FOR ANY CLAIM, DAMAGES OR OTHER
LIABILITY, WHETHER IN AN ACTION OF CONTRACT, TORT OR OTHERWISE, ARISING FROM,
OUT OF OR IN CONNECTION WITH THE SOFTWARE OR THE USE OR OTHER DEALINGS IN THE
SOFTWARE.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Games</title>
      <link>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/games/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 May 2016 22:31:58 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/games/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Spectrum games are available for use in emulators in a number of file formats, the most popular ones being
Z80, TAP and TZX, all of which Plus-F can load. TAP files are at present the most reliable, although you should be able
to use a lot of Z80 and TZX files as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most authoritative sources for Spectrum games the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.worldofspectrum.org/archive.html&#34;&gt;World of Spectrum Archive&lt;/a&gt;,
which has an extensive collection of TAP and TZX files.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t forget that the classic Spectrum games we can play today on emulators remain the result of the skills and
dedication of the programmers who developed them. While many have granted free distribution rights for their games,
others have not, and it is their right to do so. As such, please be considerate when downloading emulator files,
and refer to the information &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.worldofspectrum.org/permits&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.worldofspectrum.org/permits/publishers.html&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.worldofspectrum.org/permits/individuals.html&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;
for full details on which publishers and developers have granted free distribution rights.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Emulator</title>
      <link>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/emulator/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 May 2016 22:31:58 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/emulator/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;The Plus-F Emulator can emulate either a 48k Spectrum or a Spectrum +2, and can load games from TAP, TZX or Z80 format files (TAP files have the best support). At present there is no sound support, and the graphics timing is not 100% accurate, so don&amp;rsquo;t expect programs which generate &amp;ldquo;rainbow&amp;rdquo; effects to work properly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;so-where-is-the-symbol-shift-key&#34;&gt;So where is the symbol shift key?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The CTRL key is used in place of the Spectrum&amp;rsquo;s symbol shift key.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-to-use-it&#34;&gt;How to use it&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Emulator is controlled by the options in the menu bar at the top of the screen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;file-menu&#34;&gt;File menu&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Open: Open a TAP, TZX or Z80 file.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Z80 files will start automatically. To load from a TAP or TZX file, type LOAD &amp;ldquo;&amp;rdquo; (key J then symbol shift+P twice) in
Spectrum BASIC, and then choose Play from the Tape menu.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Quit: Quit the Emulator.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;computer-menu&#34;&gt;Computer menu&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reset: Reset the Emulator (just like pulling the plug out and putting it back in again).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Host Joystick: Select this option to emulate a Sinclair 1 joystick through the keyboard. Controls are not redefinable and are fixed to the conventional ones below:

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Q: Up&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A: Down&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;O: Left&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;P: Right&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;M: Fire&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Model: Choose the model of Spectrum to emulate, either 48k or +2. Changing the model will reset the Emulator.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Speed: Choose the speed the Emulator runs at:

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Normal: The same speed as a real Spectrum.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fast: 1.5 times the speed of a real Spectrum.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Double: Double the speed of a real Spectrum.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Turbo: Much, much faster than a real Spectrum. Use this if you&amp;rsquo;re bored waiting for TAP or TZX files to load.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;tape-menu&#34;&gt;Tape menu&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The controls on the tape menu are also displayed on buttons at the bottom of the Emulator window. The tape icon turns
green to indicate when the tape is playing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Play: Play a TAP or TZX file.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stop: Stop the tape.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rewind to Start: Rewind to the start of the current tape.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tape Information: Shows information embedded in the tape file, if any.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jump to Block: Jump to a particular block of the tape.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;network-menu&#34;&gt;Network menu&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Connect: Enter a connection code to pair up with a Guest for a two-player gaming session.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Disconnect: Disconnect from a Guest to stop a two-player gaming session.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Guest</title>
      <link>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/guest/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 May 2016 22:31:58 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/guest/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;The Plus-F Guest is a program that receives screen updates from a Plus-F Emulator across a network, and sends back
keypresses translated to Kempston joystick movements. This means that a user of the guest can participate in a
two-player game, provided the game has Kempston joystick support (most have).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;keyboard-controls&#34;&gt;Keyboard Controls&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At present, controls are not redefinable and are fixed to the conventional ones below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Q: Up&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A: Down&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;O: Left&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;P: Right&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;M: Fire&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;menu-items&#34;&gt;Menu items&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Guest can also be controlled by the options in the menu bar at the top of the screen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;file-menu&#34;&gt;File menu&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Quit: Quit the Guest&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;network-menu&#34;&gt;Network menu&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Connect: Enter a connection code to pair up with an Emulator for a two-player gaming session.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Disconnect: Disconnect from an Emulator to stop a two-player gaming session.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>