<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Plus-F</title>
    <link>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content on Plus-F</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 18 Dec 2016 22:27:26 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://plusf.socialthingy.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Version 1.2</title>
      <link>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/release-notes/1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 18 Dec 2016 22:27:26 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/release-notes/1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Added full-screen mode and rendering tweaks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Minor bugfix to tape loading.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Going Too Quickly, Working Too Hard</title>
      <link>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/blog/optimisation/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Dec 2016 21:24:44 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/blog/optimisation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The just-about-holding-together addition of tape loading emulation I told you about
&lt;a href=&#34;../if-you-only-do-one-thing&#34;&gt;last time&lt;/a&gt; was the last but one of the major bits
of +F. Having reached this milestone, I decided to take some time out and enjoy
playing a game or two of Match Day II before doing any more work on it. My work
may have stopped, but it turns out my computer was working as hard as ever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The user experience was fairly good, at first glance, with the emulation running
without crashes and at full speed. Indeed, I&amp;rsquo;d even had time to add a &amp;ldquo;turbo&amp;rdquo; mode
which would run the emulation as fast as possible, designed to remove the boredom
of waiting for tapes to load (although this does give a somewhat less authentic
experience and you should hang your head in shame if you do use it). The problem
was that when I had +F running for more than a couple of minutes, the fan on
my laptop would whoosh up to full speed, and stay there more or less until +F
stopped. A quick check with &lt;code&gt;top&lt;/code&gt; confirmed that +F was using a whole core of
the laptop&amp;rsquo;s dual-core processor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By any measure, that&amp;rsquo;s too much for a Spectrum emulator running on modern hardware.
The &lt;a href=&#34;../standing-on-the-shoulders-of-giants&#34;&gt;FUSE&lt;/a&gt; emulator written in C uses only
a few percent of the available CPU capacity on the same computer and OS, and while
I wasn&amp;rsquo;t expecting to achieve that level of performance from a Java application
(a deliberate trade-off of raw performance for fewer cross-platform difficulties),
I was still surprised it was quite so processor-hungry. But why?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll spare you the blow-by-blow details, except to say that a few profiling
sessions using &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/RichardWarburton/honest-profiler/wiki&#34;&gt;honest-profiler&lt;/a&gt;
showed that the problem lay in the rendering of the display. The antiquated display
hardware of the Spectrum was efficient both in terms of memory and execution time
(while also giving us the famous &lt;a href=&#34;http://speccyholic.tumblr.com/post/89194660510/the-spectrums-secret-weapon&#34;&gt;attribute clash&lt;/a&gt;)
but does make it slightly convoluted to generate a pixel-based RGB bitmap. Somewhere
in that display emulation were a few methods in particular that appeared to be hogging
the CPU unexpectedly. The surprising thing is that these methods did little else
apart from looking up various mappings between Spectrum display co-ordinates and
the corresponding window co-ordinates. Thinking ahead, I&amp;rsquo;d decided to pre-compute
these calculations and store the results in an array, since they&amp;rsquo;d be needed on
every single display refresh, so I couldn&amp;rsquo;t see why these would be slow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And there was my mistake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d assumed that array lookups are less expensive than repeated method calls, but
that wasn&amp;rsquo;t actually the case for the calculations that I had precomputed. When
you include bounds checking and whatever else is involved in array access, it
actually turned out to be &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; expensive than recalculating the co-ordinates on
every call. In trying to outsmart the JVM with some optimisations of my own, I&amp;rsquo;d
actually worked against it and stopped it from doing its own, more effective, optimisations
to the code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the JVM is very clever indeed. (It does this sort of thing all day, every day, so
it ought to be an expert, I suppose.) Based on the methods it sees being executed
as your program runs, it can choose to compile and inline them as it sees fit. Inlining
in particular tends to work best where methods are short, with the upshot that
&lt;a href=&#34;https://techblug.wordpress.com/2013/08/19/java-jit-compiler-inlining/&#34;&gt;adding method calls can make your code run faster&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, when it comes to Java code, you could argue that you&amp;rsquo;re better to start
off with code that composes lots of calls to small methods anyway, and you&amp;rsquo;d be
right. If nothing else, it means that your code is easier to reason about and test,
but as an added bonus you&amp;rsquo;re also staying out of the JVM&amp;rsquo;s way and letting it do
what it&amp;rsquo;s best at.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mistake I made is one which has been known for a long time, and which &lt;a href=&#34;https://shreevatsa.wordpress.com/2008/05/16/premature-optimization-is-the-root-of-all-evil/&#34;&gt;Knuth&lt;/a&gt;
popularised with his statement &lt;em&gt;premature optimisation is the root of all evil&lt;/em&gt;.
Software may have moved on in many ways since he said that in 1974, but to me the
problem of premature optimisation is more human than technological, and I&amp;rsquo;d be surprised
if we were that much less susceptible to it now than we were then. In my case,
with no evidence to support me, I assumed that certain operations were going to
be costly, and wrote bad code based on that faulty assumption.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How could I have avoided this?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s a tricky balance. On the one hand, in my original Python implementation of
+F, by doing no profiling or performance testing until the very end, &lt;a href=&#34;../fundamentals&#34;&gt;I ended
up wasting time on an implementation that would never have been fit for purpose&lt;/a&gt;. Clearly, I could have done with paying a bit more attention to
performance up-front in that case. In the case of the Java version of +F, by
fixating on performance too early (probably a consequence of having been burned
a little by the fact the first attempt at +F was so slow), I ended up with an
inefficient application.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think it all boils down to gathering evidence and acting upon that. Where you
have requirements that a program should exhibit a certain level of performance
(in my case not needing an entire CPU core in order to emulate a computerised beermat
from the 1980s), it&amp;rsquo;s important to test for this, just like you would test whether
it behaves correctly or not, and to bake this testing into your development cycle
if you can.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>If You Only Do One Thing</title>
      <link>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/blog/if-you-only-do-one-thing/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Nov 2016 23:25:34 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/blog/if-you-only-do-one-thing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Over the years, there have been all number of innovations, techniques, tools,
tricks and fads purported to help you build better-quality applications more quickly - model-driven code generation,
object-relational frameworks, IoC containers, unit testing, Scrum, Kanban, documenting everything, documenting nothing,
pair programming - even industrial quantities of XML (in the case of the abomination that was SOAP). For me, though,
one stands head and shoulders above all the rest, Test-Driven Development. If you only do one thing tomorrow that you
aren&amp;rsquo;t doing today, choose TDD.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I came to the TDD party pretty late. Of course, I&amp;rsquo;d known all about unit testing for a long time, but
I&amp;rsquo;d never actually seen it work, in terms of improving the speed or quality of application development. What I&amp;rsquo;d
generally seen was that a conscientious newcomer to some team would write tests for new code they were working on, plus
maybe a few other tests where they had to fix existing code. Those tests would be maintained for a period of time,
before falling into (for want of a better word) disrepair, spending as much time failing as passing, and eventually
being deleted or ignored. When I first came into a TDD environment, it opened my eyes to how to make proper use of
automated tests, and when I look back at the times before I used TDD, I see nothing but missed opportunities to build
better software.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve done TDD with JUnit, ScalaTest, PyTest, Nose and Cucumber, and it works well with any and all of them. I don&amp;rsquo;t
think the choice of tools is especially important - just pick the ones that work for you and use them. Even if you&amp;rsquo;re
still writing programs in COBOL for mainframes, I&amp;rsquo;m sure there are options out there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t think I would have attempted +F if I wasn&amp;rsquo;t already doing TDD in my day job. A processor is basically a
large collection of instructions which all operate on the same global state. Those instructions can then be combined in
an infinite number of permutations, where the state of a single bit in a single register can cause execution to take a
completely different path. Butterflies flap their wings at every step along the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I shuddered at the thought of having to debug a problem in some large Z80 program (i.e. Match Day II) without having
confidence that the individual processor operations were working correctly in isolation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only way to tackle it was one operation at a time, writing tests based on what the
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.z80.info/zip/z80cpu_um.pdf&#34;&gt;Z80 User Manual&lt;/a&gt; specified, writing the code for the operation, then moving on
to the next. Dull, yes, but it&amp;rsquo;s the only way I could see of gaining any traction. As it is, having taken the TDD
approach, the major problems which stopped programs from working outright have been reasonably rare, obvious and easy to
debug and fix.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By now, you may have read about my &lt;a href=&#34;../fundamentals&#34;&gt;valiant but doomed attempt to write +F in Python&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;ll confess that
the thought of having to start again from scratch did make me think twice about what I was doing, but the choice was made
easier by the one thing I had in my favour - a good set of tests for all of the processor emulation. And, given that I
hadn&amp;rsquo;t got much beyond that part (aside from a prototype display that showed just how slow the emulator was), that meant
I had a good set of tests for more or less everything that I needed to rewrite. Admittedly, those tests were in Python&amp;rsquo;s
&lt;a href=&#34;https://nose.readthedocs.io/en/latest/&#34;&gt;Nose framework&lt;/a&gt;, but picking up on something else I&amp;rsquo;d learned over the previous
year or two, a typical test looked like this one:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;def test_and_a_with_other_reg_giving_zero_result(self):
    # given
    self.given_register_contains_value(&#39;a&#39;, 0b10101010)
    self.given_register_contains_value(&#39;b&#39;, 0b01010101)

    self.given_next_instruction_is(0xa0)

    # when
    self.processor.execute()

    # then
    self.assert_register(&#39;a&#39;).equals(0b00000000)
    self.assert_register(&#39;b&#39;).equals(0b01010101)

    self.assert_flag(&#39;s&#39;).is_reset()
    self.assert_flag(&#39;z&#39;).is_set()
    self.assert_flag(&#39;h&#39;).is_set()
    self.assert_flag(&#39;p&#39;).is_set()
    self.assert_flag(&#39;n&#39;).is_reset()
    self.assert_flag(&#39;c&#39;).is_reset()
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words, it read sort of like a mini-DSL. A bit of judicious search-and-replace meant that I could port tests
like these easily to an equivalent in ScalaTest like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-scala&#34;&gt;&amp;quot;and &amp;lt;reg&amp;gt;&amp;quot; should &amp;quot;calculate a zero result when a and &amp;lt;reg&amp;gt; have no shared bits&amp;quot; in new Machine {
  // given
  registerContainsValue(&amp;quot;a&amp;quot;, binary(&amp;quot;10101010&amp;quot;))
  registerContainsValue(&amp;quot;b&amp;quot;, binary(&amp;quot;01010101&amp;quot;))

  nextInstructionIs(0xa0)

  // when
  processor.execute()

  // then
  registerValue(&amp;quot;a&amp;quot;) shouldBe binary(&amp;quot;00000000&amp;quot;)
  registerValue(&amp;quot;b&amp;quot;) shouldBe binary(&amp;quot;01010101&amp;quot;)

  flag(&amp;quot;s&amp;quot;).value shouldBe false
  flag(&amp;quot;z&amp;quot;).value shouldBe true
  flag(&amp;quot;h&amp;quot;).value shouldBe true
  flag(&amp;quot;p&amp;quot;).value shouldBe true
  flag(&amp;quot;n&amp;quot;).value shouldBe false
  flag(&amp;quot;c&amp;quot;).value shouldBe false
  flag(&amp;quot;f3&amp;quot;).value shouldBe false
  flag(&amp;quot;f5&amp;quot;).value shouldBe false
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All I then had to do was write the implementation of the DSL (easy enough), and then I had a full set of tests
available from the outset, against which I could code the Java version of +F. Class-by-class, I converted
the tests and then wrote the code to pass them, and in little over a month I was back to the same point I&amp;rsquo;d reached in
Python without too much effort. Full-on TDD to the rescue!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, it would be out of character if the faint glimmer of success I saw in the distance wasn&amp;rsquo;t subsequently
extinguished by an act of stupidity, laziness, or (in this case) both.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Processor emulation isn&amp;rsquo;t the only complex thing I had to tackle when writing +F. Tape loading was another
tricky area, and emulating it properly is surprisingly fiddly. There&amp;rsquo;s a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.worldofspectrum.org/TZXformat.html&#34;&gt;remarkably well-documented specification&lt;/a&gt; of the TZX emulated tape format, and in theory all that&amp;rsquo;s required is
to turn the contents of a TZX file into a stream of 0s and 1s which can be fed bit-by-bit into the emulated Spectrum.
The catch is that the timings and high/low state of the input really have to be precise, or the ROM&amp;rsquo;s tape loading
routine doesn&amp;rsquo;t work. Either the input signal won&amp;rsquo;t be recognised at all, or you&amp;rsquo;re faced with the sight of the
&lt;code&gt;R Tape Loading Error, 0:1&lt;/code&gt; error message that haunted the childhood of me and many others of my generation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Intricate and nuanced, but well-documented &amp;hellip; this is exactly the sort of thing that TDD was made for. However, by this
stage, I had a lot of +F working and I&amp;rsquo;d become a bit cavalier in my attitude again. (My unfortunate dalliance with
Python was by this stage some six months in the past. How quickly the mind forgets.) Certain that I was only a few commits
away from a fully-working application, I pinned my ears back and frenziedly wrote the TZX-handling routines, supported by
only a smattering of tests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Surprisingly, the code worked. Sadly, however, it was laughably inefficient. When reading from a TZX file, the screen
refresh rate would slow noticeably, and I&amp;rsquo;m sure all the lights in the house became dimmer while it was running too. It&amp;rsquo;s
hardly unheard of first implementations to be lacking performance-wise, so I could treat it as a proof of concept and
rewrite it piece-by-piece so that it skipped along more efficiently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s where the problems &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; began. Inefficient as it may have been, the first TZX routine was fairly good functionally.
But because I didn&amp;rsquo;t have a thorough set of tests which allowed me to make changes and still verify that each part worked,
any time I did something that made it run faster, I also introduced a bug somewhere else. In a bid to stop the incessant
cycle of fixing one bug only to introduce another, I resorted to cobbling together a &amp;ldquo;regression test&amp;rdquo; based
on &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/alangibson27/+F/blob/master/+F/src/test/java/com/socialthingy/plusf/tape/ReferenceVariableSpeedBlock.java&#34;&gt;this class from the original, inefficient, implementation&lt;/a&gt;
and testing all of my potential improvements with respect to that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It helped, but was nothing more than a length of wallpaper to cover up the cracks in my approach. It&amp;rsquo;s still there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thankfully, I haven&amp;rsquo;t had to touch the TZX-handling routines much of late, but I dread the day that I have to. I think
it&amp;rsquo;s pretty clear to see, when comparing &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/alangibson27/+F/tree/master/+F/src/main/java/com/socialthingy/plusf/tape&#34;&gt;its code&lt;/a&gt;
with the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/alangibson27/+F/tree/master/+F/src/main/java/com/socialthingy/plusf/z80&#34;&gt;Z80 emulation code that was developed with a TDD approach&lt;/a&gt;,
that not building it by TDD has caused a lot of problems there needn&amp;rsquo;t have been.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lesson? It&amp;rsquo;s all too easy to consider brushing TDD aside in an effort to get to where you want to be more quickly,
but no matter how much you try to rationalise it, it&amp;rsquo;s still just cutting corners. You can&amp;rsquo;t just wave away the inherent
complexity of software when it suits, but you can certainly use TDD to tame it a bit.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Version 1.1</title>
      <link>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/release-notes/1/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Nov 2016 22:27:26 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/release-notes/1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Single launcher for Emulator and Guest&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;UI tweaks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Windows 64-bit Installer and Universal Zip downloads&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Fundamentals are Important</title>
      <link>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/blog/fundamentals/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Nov 2016 22:43:30 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/blog/fundamentals/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The relationship between a programmer and a language is much like the relationship between the cricketer and a
bat. Unless you know how to handle it properly, you&amp;rsquo;re not going to achieve much and you could end up in a lot of pain.
And so it was with +F, or at least the program which eventually became +F. It started off with the working title
&lt;em&gt;QAOPM&lt;/em&gt;, and was written in Python.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The choice of language was driven by a couple of things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, I aimed to write a cross-platform emulator. Python is readily available on both of my target platforms (Linux and
Windows), and I planned to use the Pygame library to build the user interface. Second, I love Python&amp;rsquo;s
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.python.org/dev/peps/pep-0020/&#34;&gt;principles&lt;/a&gt;, its elegance and its clarity. (I know the fact that whitespace
is syntactically relevant bothers some people, but it looks natural to me, and it&amp;rsquo;s never tripped me up.) My
opportunities to work with this language had been limited to a few utilities and the odd simple web application,
and I relished the chance to learn more on a project that was a bit more meaty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That decision made, I set about writing +F, and four enjoyable months later (well, as enjoyable as jumping armpits-deep
into the Z80 reference manual can be) I had a basic working version which could load a program from a snapshot file,
emulate the Z80 and render the Spectrum display. It couldn&amp;rsquo;t accept keyboard input so you couldn&amp;rsquo;t actually do much with
it, but I was sure that would follow in short order. All the unit tests worked, the display rendering was accurate,
and it was time to fire it all up together for the first time and give it a shakedown.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And &amp;hellip; it was slow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not a little sluggish, not jerky from time to time, but truly, painfully slow. Right from the outset, I&amp;rsquo;d been sure
that a modern PC (even my 2010-vintage laptop) would be able to handle emulation of an 8-bit computer without breaking
sweat. After all, there&amp;rsquo;s already an &lt;a href=&#34;http://torinak.com/qaop&#34;&gt;emulator written in JavaScript&lt;/a&gt; that runs at full speed
in a browser, so while I was expecting I&amp;rsquo;d need to make a few tweaks here and there, I had just assumed that the emulator
would be fast enough. Not so. What was the problem?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not Python. Definitely not Python.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(At this point, I want to make perfectly clear that I&amp;rsquo;m certain that in the hands of an experienced Python programmer,
it is possible to write an emulator with the requisite speed to be usable. If that sounds like you, I&amp;rsquo;ve left all of
the code for the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/alangibson27/qaopm&#34;&gt;Python +F on GitHub&lt;/a&gt;, and in the interests of learning how to
become a better programmer, I&amp;rsquo;d be very happy if you had the time to take a look and could explain to me how I could
have achieved a better outcome. I&amp;rsquo;m not having a bash at Python, I&amp;rsquo;m having a bash at me.)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve earned a living for almost two decades writing software in Java, and more recently Scala. I&amp;rsquo;ve become to an
extent conditioned to think of software solutions in terms of interactions between objects (although obviously Scala
opens the door to a more functional approach too), and that&amp;rsquo;s how I approached the Python predecessor of +F.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The processor was a class. Each Z80 operation was a class, with related operations existing in a class hierarchy. Memory was
a class. The display was a class. Almost everything was nicely organised into classes, each with short methods which
did strictly one thing - just the way you&amp;rsquo;d unthinkingly build almost any Java application. For all
that I could read and write Python, though, I&amp;rsquo;d neglected the fact that an interpreted, dynamically-typed language
behaves differently to a compiled, statically-typed language.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out this was a really big problem for me because my code fell foul of a combination of Python&amp;rsquo;s weak spots (according to
&lt;a href=&#34;https://wiki.python.org/moin/PythonSpeed/PerformanceTips#Loops&#34;&gt;this page&lt;/a&gt;) - lots of field dereferencing in tight, nested for-loops.
In any other application, I may not have noticed this, but an emulator is basically just one big outer loop, which runs some
other loops inside it on each iteration. The outermost loop runs once for each display refresh cycle (50 times a second
in the case of the Spectrum), with each iteration running the processor&amp;rsquo;s fetch-execute cycle up to about 17000 times,
followed by another loop which sets the colour of each of the 49152 pixels in the display. Lots of for-loops and, in
my implementation, lots of dereferencing of fields on collaborating objects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s a representative example of how the code for a single emulated Z80 operation (&lt;code&gt;add a, (hl)&lt;/code&gt;) looked, before I
realised this there were going to be speed issues:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;class OpAddAHlIndirect(BaseOp):
    def __init__(self, processor, memory):
        BaseOp.__init__(self)
        self.processor = processor
        self.memory = memory

    def execute(self):
        value = self.memory.peek(self.processor.get_16bit_reg(&#39;hl&#39;))
        _add_a(self.processor, value, False)

    def t_states(self):
        return 7

    def __str__(self):
        return &#39;add a, (hl)&#39;

def _add_a(processor, value, carry):
    signed_a = to_signed(processor.main_registers[&#39;a&#39;])
    if carry:
        value = (value + 1) &amp;amp; 0xff
    result, half_carry, full_carry = bitwise_add(processor.main_registers[&#39;a&#39;], value)
    signed_result = to_signed(result)
    processor.main_registers[&#39;a&#39;] = result
    processor.set_condition(&#39;s&#39;, signed_result &amp;lt; 0)
    processor.set_condition(&#39;z&#39;, result == 0)
    processor.set_condition(&#39;h&#39;, half_carry)
    processor.set_condition(&#39;p&#39;, (signed_a &amp;lt; 0) != (signed_result &amp;lt; 0))
    processor.set_condition(&#39;n&#39;, False)
    processor.set_condition(&#39;c&#39;, full_carry)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The execute method is the one that is run in the emulation loop. This single method, which could in theory be executed
up to 17000 times every 1/50th of a second, was itself doing three expensive field dereferences per iteration, and when
you include those done by the &lt;code&gt;_add_a&lt;/code&gt; function it invokes, in total there are about a dozen in executing this one simple
operation!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having gone back and done the background reading I ought to have done at the start, I spent a month trying to remedy the
problem, the outcome of which was that the code for our representative &lt;code&gt;add a, (hl)&lt;/code&gt; operation became &amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;class OpAddAHlIndirect(BaseOp):
    def __init__(self, processor, memory):
        BaseOp.__init__(self)
        self.processor = processor
        self.memory = memory

    def execute(self, processor, memory, pc):
        value = memory[0xffff &amp;amp; processor.get_16bit_reg(&#39;hl&#39;)]
        _add_a(processor, value, False)
        return 7, False, pc

    def __str__(self):
        return &#39;add a, (hl)&#39;

def _add_a(processor, value, carry):
    signed_a = to_signed(processor.main_registers[&#39;a&#39;])
    if carry:
        value = (value + 1) &amp;amp; 0xff
    result, half_carry, full_carry = bitwise_add(processor.main_registers[&#39;a&#39;], value)
    signed_result = to_signed(result)
    processor.main_registers[&#39;a&#39;] = result
    set_condition = processor.set_condition
    set_condition(&#39;s&#39;, signed_result &amp;lt; 0)
    set_condition(&#39;z&#39;, result == 0)
    set_condition(&#39;h&#39;, half_carry)
    set_condition(&#39;p&#39;, (signed_a &amp;lt; 0) != (signed_result &amp;lt; 0))
    set_condition(&#39;n&#39;, False)
    set_condition(&#39;c&#39;, full_carry)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;hellip; and while reducing the number of dot-dereferences (complemented with a few other recommended techniques such as
flattening nested loops) did help a bit, it wasn&amp;rsquo;t enough to make the emulator fast enough to be viable. Suitably
discouraged, I decided to scrap the idea of writing an emulator in Python and retreated to the safer territory of Java.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where had I gone wrong?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had my cricket bat, I&amp;rsquo;d carefully seasoned it with linseed oil and I&amp;rsquo;d spent my time in the nets, honing my technique.
I&amp;rsquo;d then tried to play snooker with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hadn&amp;rsquo;t understood the fundamentals of Python. You most certainly &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; write Java-esque object-oriented programs with
it, but what is cheap in Java comes with a different cost in Python. I fell into a trap
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.joelonsoftware.com/articles/fog0000000319.html&#34;&gt;articulately described by Joel Spolsky&lt;/a&gt;, where I didn&amp;rsquo;t
see the details beneath an abstraction, and paid the price in terms of poor performance. (If you haven&amp;rsquo;t read that
article yet, stop right now, read and understand it, read it again, then read some of the other articles on Joel on Software
before coming back here. It&amp;rsquo;ll be well worth your while, trust me.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope I won&amp;rsquo;t make this particular mistake again, but how could I have avoided this problem? I could have read some
information about the performance characteristics of Python in advance of starting, of course. But given that I&amp;rsquo;m not
especially taken with the idea of lots of up-front background reading when there&amp;rsquo;s code I could be writing (this may or
may not be a character flaw, I leave that for you to judge), I think the best thing I could have done is reached a point
where I realised my mistake a lot sooner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Premature optimisation is of course a problem in itself (more on &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; later), but a spot of up-front prototyping would have
definitely helped. For example, I could have built a representative subset of the Z80 instruction set and performance
tested a few simple routines, or built the display rendering logic and tested it standalone at the required frame rate.
I&amp;rsquo;m sure that either of these would have made me either change the way I was writing my Python, or make the jump to
Java sooner than I did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In honesty, it would have been easy to give up once I realised my best chance was to start all over again, but I did
have one thing in my favour which was going to ease the pain considerably. I&amp;rsquo;ll tell you about that next time.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Seeing Clearly</title>
      <link>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/blog/seeing-clearly/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 06 Nov 2016 22:02:33 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/blog/seeing-clearly/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Before I dive into the missteps and mishaps of +F, I&amp;rsquo;d like to start with one very important thing I did right,
in the very early stages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The original idea for +F came from the tail end of an IM conversation with an old school friend, reminiscing
about the computer games we used to play when we were young. A particular favourite of ours was Match Day II
(for those of you too young to remember, it was sort of like the best bits of FIFA and PES combined in a single game,
only about a hundred times better than that) and we were at the time convinced we would be world champions at it,
if such a competition had existed. (Sadly, eSports wasn&amp;rsquo;t to come into being until a good 10 years after we were past
our gaming peak, and the world had mistakenly moved on from Match Day II by then anyway.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can&amp;rsquo;t remember who, but one or the other of us signed off by saying &lt;em&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m sure I could still hammer you&lt;/em&gt;, and
it put me to thinking &amp;hellip; which one of us would actually win? The simple way to solve it would be to get together
in front of a computer, fire up an emulator (FUSE, for example) and sort it out. Sadly, at the time, we were
on almost exactly opposite sides of the world, and it would have been a long way for either of us to fly simply
to settle an old childhood rivalry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nonetheless, it planted an idea in my mind. Given how easy it is to make high quality video calls to faraway
places, surely there must be no problem in sending Spectrum screenshots in one direction and joystick movements
in another, at least in theory? Depending on the distance and quality of network connection, things might chug
along a little slowly at times, but the Spectrum was never known as a speed machine, was it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I toyed with the idea for a while before I started any code. My first thought was whether I could bolt some
network play facilities onto an existing open-source emulator, most of which tend to be written in C or some
similar low-level language. I rejected this idea primarily because I thought trying to understand someone
else&amp;rsquo;s C code would be beyond me, but also because I wanted the emulator to be usable across Linux and
Windows, and a language with simpler cross-platform support would be a better option.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So that more or less put me in the position of writing my own emulator from the ground up. It&amp;rsquo;s a challenge I
did relish, but I wasn&amp;rsquo;t in any illusion about the amount of work it would need. Where to start?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More importantly, where to &lt;em&gt;stop&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I only wanted to be able to play a couple of games of Match Day II, so there wouldn&amp;rsquo;t be any need to go overboard
with whizzbang features that made no difference to the quality of gameplay. Those thoughts left me with a very clear
vision of what I wanted +F to be:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An emulator that worked on (at least) Linux and Windows.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Network play capability, with a fully-fledged emulator at one end and a &amp;ldquo;dumb&amp;rdquo; console at the other.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;48k model only.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Allows a full game of Match Day II to be played without crashing, even if nothing else works.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No sound.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No loading borders.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No superfluous UI features or twiddles.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And there it was, the minimum viable product for +F. I didn&amp;rsquo;t go as far as setting up a backlog for it or
anything like that, but armed with a clear idea of what I wanted, I was able to decide where to start, what to do
next, and what not to bother with. That&amp;rsquo;s really important, because even in something with a scope that seems
limited, like a Spectrum emulator, there are a lot more things going on than you might expect, and a lot of
places you could choose to put your effort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take borders. It&amp;rsquo;s possible to change the colour of the border at specific positions down the screen, and
indeed games like &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.worldofspectrum.org/infoseekid.cgi?id=0000227&#34;&gt;Aquaplane&lt;/a&gt; use this to create a
&amp;ldquo;horizon&amp;rdquo; effect that spans the full width of the screen. However, making the change at the correct position
is intimately linked with the timing of the Spectrum&amp;rsquo;s display hardware. The rules for emulating this correctly
are &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.worldofspectrum.org/faq/reference/48kreference.htm#ZXSpectrum&#34;&gt;very complicated&lt;/a&gt; and would take
an age to implement and test.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For my purposes, though, because I had already established Match Day II was my priority, and because it
doesn&amp;rsquo;t do anything at all the border (it&amp;rsquo;s black the whole time) it was an easy choice for me not to care
about this at all. This sort of focus that I had because of my clear vision of +F saved me from
disappearing off into the more arcane (but no less technically interesting) aspects of building an emulator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How does any of this relate to what you and I do in our day jobs? Well, imagine you&amp;rsquo;re maintaining a library
that&amp;rsquo;s going to be used by some other groups - maybe internal, maybe external, maybe a combination of both.
Once your code has been released into the wild for the first time, you&amp;rsquo;re bound to get people coming to you and
asking for new features. Chances are they&amp;rsquo;ll all request different things - this team wants something that
makes it easier to integrate with Spring, that team wants support for a particular metrics framework, and that
team over there wants a version that produces XML rather than JSON.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reasonable though all these requests may be, if you say &lt;em&gt;yes&lt;/em&gt; to all of them, you&amp;rsquo;ll end up with a bloated
library, it&amp;rsquo;ll be more involved to maintain and release, client teams will have a tougher time to upgrade,
and in the end every encounter with your library will become a chore rather than a pleasure. You&amp;rsquo;ll also run
the risk of losing focus on the core capabilities of your library, and you&amp;rsquo;ll spend time and effort on things
that only a fraction of your user base will use, rather than using that time to make your code more robust,
correct, efficient or easy to integrate with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end, it comes down to one thing - do you have a clear idea of what the core purpose of your library is?
Sure, you could add some code that will produce an XML form of your output, and the people who asked for it
will doubtless be thankful (today, anyway). But should your library really be getting involved in those sort of
serialisation issues - maybe it should be producing a logical model and leaving it up to the teams who use it
to decide how its output appears instead?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe adding the XML support (or whatever) &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; absolutely the right thing to do, but that&amp;rsquo;s a question only
you (and the rest of your team) can answer. If you&amp;rsquo;re given a requirement and you can&amp;rsquo;t answer the question
&lt;em&gt;Do we need this?&lt;/em&gt; with a straight &lt;em&gt;yes&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;no&lt;/em&gt;, it&amp;rsquo;s well worth your time to figure out why you can&amp;rsquo;t.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Standing on the Shoulders of Giants</title>
      <link>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/blog/standing-on-the-shoulders-of-giants/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Nov 2016 20:54:07 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/blog/standing-on-the-shoulders-of-giants/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The fundamental thing an emulator does is, by definition, copy the behaviour of something else. And so it is
with +F, which emulates a real ZX Spectrum. The catch, sadly, is that I don&amp;rsquo;t have one of those to hand, so
without the real thing as a reference, how can I check that +F is working properly? The answer lies in the
fantastic emulators that others have written.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I mainly run Linux at home, and over the years I&amp;rsquo;ve enjoyed using the &lt;a href=&#34;http://fuse-emulator.sourceforge.net/&#34;&gt;FUSE Emulator&lt;/a&gt;.
From my time using it, I&amp;rsquo;ve developed confidence that it is a faithful emulation of a ZX Spectrum, and at
various points in the development of +F I&amp;rsquo;ve used it as my reference. When I wasn&amp;rsquo;t sure if my Z80 emulation
code was setting flags correctly, or I wanted to see what the behaviour of a particular block of assembly code
was, I would run identical tests against FUSE and +F, and where +F gave a different answer, I could be confident
that there was a bug in there which I needed to fix.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On top of that, FUSE also comes with a handy set of debugging tools, which I also made use of at various times -
notably in checking I had the right behaviour for incrementing the value of the refresh register. (There was also
another time where I poured away days of effort trying to squash a bug I&amp;rsquo;d introduced unthinkingly as a
result of the fundamental misconception that the Spectrum ROM would never try to overwrite itself, but more
on that later.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of this is simply to say that, without FUSE, I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t have been able to develop +F. While +F does have
a few tweaks and twiddles that FUSE doesn&amp;rsquo;t have, it&amp;rsquo;s still inferior in many ways, and if you&amp;rsquo;re looking for a
solid Spectrum emulator that&amp;rsquo;s packed full of features and gives you an authentic experience, try FUSE.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also goes without saying that I&amp;rsquo;m deeply thankful to FUSE&amp;rsquo;s author for his work, and also very much in awe
of it.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>In The Beginning</title>
      <link>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/blog/in-the-beginning/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Oct 2016 22:49:58 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/blog/in-the-beginning/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Why did I bother writing +F? There are already plenty of fully-featured, freely-available Spectrum emulators for
more or less any platform you care to think of. Indeed, I remember using a perfectly playable one on the Commodore
Amiga as far back as 1994 or 1995 (ZXAM by Antonio J. Pomar Roselló), so it&amp;rsquo;s hardly a novel idea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did have a little twist which I wanted to add, which at the time I started writing didn&amp;rsquo;t appear to be available
in any other emulator, namely the ability to play games across the Internet. (It turns out that &lt;a href=&#34;http://zxm.speccy.cz/realspec/&#34;&gt;RealSpec&lt;/a&gt;
claims to do this and more, but I haven&amp;rsquo;t tried it.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More than just that, though, it was probably inevitable I would end up trying this sooner or later. Much like
mountaineers are reputed to climb mountains &amp;ldquo;because they&amp;rsquo;re there&amp;rdquo;, or lovelorn teenage boys write dreadful and
embarrassing poetry, the chances of a programming geek with a fondness for 80s gaming writing an emulator are
rather high. (Given I&amp;rsquo;d already written a
&lt;a href=&#34;https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/speccy-loading-borders/jakeajfeddddpglibndhjhdmlinejihf&#34;&gt;Chrome plugin that uses CSS to emulate Spectrum loading borders&lt;/a&gt;,
it&amp;rsquo;s safe to say that I&amp;rsquo;ve got form.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;So Mr. Nerdy-Nerdy has a warm, fuzzy feeling about his pet project&lt;/em&gt;, you may be thinking. &lt;em&gt;Very good, move along.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And to a certain extent, you&amp;rsquo;re right. There&amp;rsquo;s nothing novel about +F and I certainly wasn&amp;rsquo;t planning to blog about
it. Indeed, if I was just a programming geek by night, I probably wouldn&amp;rsquo;t have, but I&amp;rsquo;ve actually also been a programming
geek by profession for the best part of two decades. When you do anything for that length of time, you run the risk of
it becoming an overlearned skill, something you don&amp;rsquo;t necessarily need to devote much conscious thought to.
You learn all manner of techniques and best practices from the people you work with, you learn your own lessons, pick
your favourites, and you&amp;rsquo;ll also probably tend to adopt and fit in with the way that your team works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Combine that with time pressures and shifting requirements, and it can be easy to go through the motions and forget &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt;
you do things the way you do them. Best practices only become so because they have been shown to provide benefits,
but it&amp;rsquo;s easy to forget this and slip into something of a ritualistic mentality about the way you build software. &lt;em&gt;If our
code coverage metrics hit the magic number, we make sure the digits of our release number don&amp;rsquo;t add up to thirteen, and
we sacrifice a chicken, the software gods will smile upon us and our release will be successful.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With +F being a personal hobby project, and me being answerable to nobody but myself for its success or otherwise, I
wasn&amp;rsquo;t subject to the formalities of software development which I&amp;rsquo;ve become used to in my day job. I could completely
freely choose which ones to follow and which ones to ignore. It&amp;rsquo;s fair to say that there was a fair amount of unwarranted
bravado about the choices I made, an air of &lt;em&gt;it can&amp;rsquo;t be that complicated&lt;/em&gt; (wrong), &lt;em&gt;I do more difficult things than
this every day&lt;/em&gt; (wrong again) and &lt;em&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m old enough to know what I&amp;rsquo;m doing&lt;/em&gt; (even more wrong) about my approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The result is the catalogue of gaffes, goofs and prat-falls you&amp;rsquo;re going to read about in this blog. I will, of course,
make the odd diversion into the simultaneously mundane and fascinating details of emulation, but what I really want to
get across as I write is that there really &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; good reasons why we do things the way we do, and if we lose sight of that
then we are bound to repeat the mistakes of the past.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That does sound rather heavy and fatalistic, but the flip-side is to realise that yourself and others have already done
the hard work of figuring out how to do software well, and it&amp;rsquo;s that note of encouragement I hope you take away with you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope you find my writing enjoyable.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Version 1.0</title>
      <link>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/release-notes/1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Oct 2016 22:55:26 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/release-notes/1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Performance improvements&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;UI tweaks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Revamped network connectivity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Version 0.6</title>
      <link>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/release-notes/0/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Aug 2016 22:55:26 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/release-notes/0/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Implemented TAP and TZX support&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Added support for +2&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fixed some processor emulation bugs (there are still others in there)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Version 0.5</title>
      <link>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/release-notes/0/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 May 2016 11:47:26 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/release-notes/0/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Initial public release&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Emulation is still rather buggy (I will add fixes, but for the moment consider it the equivalent of a wobbly RAM pack
or tape loading errors!)

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reset doesn&amp;rsquo;t always work properly&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some snapshots fail to load if the Emulator has been running for some time&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 May 2016 22:31:58 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/about/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Do you remember Match Day II?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Long before FIFA, Pro Evolution Soccer or any of the others, Match Day II managed to succinctly capture the essence of
football in just 48k. No fouls, free kicks, substitutions, sendings-off or penalties - just pass, tackle, volley, head
and save. You can easily imagine how a well-worked goal in Match Day II must look much like a football purist&amp;rsquo;s idea of
perfection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, none of this was in the minds of me or my friends when we were growing up playing this Match Day II. All we
had was this compellingly playable game, and a conviction that we must be the best people in the world at playing it.
Time passes, people move on and circumstances change, but from time to time I couldn&amp;rsquo;t help but wonder what would happen
if my friends and I were to play Match Day II against each other once more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only surprise is that it took me so long to come up with the idea of +F as a way of answering that question.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Connect</title>
      <link>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/connect/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 May 2016 22:31:58 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/connect/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h3 id=&#34;how-to-do-it&#34;&gt;How to do it&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Network play works by player A running the Emulator and player B running the Guest. Both of these are downloaded and
available in the same package. Here&amp;rsquo;s how it works:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Agree on who should run the Emulator. Generally, the player with the better network upload speeds should do this.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Choose a code name and share this by email, instant message, text message or however you like.
It&amp;rsquo;s not especially important what this code is, and you can use the same one over and over again if you like.
They are only retained until the connection has been made, at which point the +F Relay Service forgets it again.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Players A and B both choose the &lt;em&gt;Connect&lt;/em&gt; option from the &lt;em&gt;Network&lt;/em&gt; menu, and enter the code name in the pop-up.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;After a short while, the pop-up should disappear and the Emulator&amp;rsquo;s screen should be shared with the Guest.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The guest can use the keys Q, A, O, P and M as a Kempston joystick controller.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Status messages below the display will show the current connection status. The colour of the message indicates the
overall quality of the connection:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Green: The connection is good enough for games to be playable.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Yellow: The connection quality is poor, and delays may be experienced.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Red: The connection has dropped, either temporarily or permanently.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;does-it-really-work&#34;&gt;Does it really work?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Limited amounts of testing on the setup below have shown that it is possible for the Emulator and the Guest to be
responsive enough to one another to make two-player games playable. Clearly, some latency may occur at times, causing
the Guest&amp;rsquo;s copy of the display to jump or jerk a little.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Emulator running on Windows 10, connected to the internet wirelessly via a non-fibre connection&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Guest running on Ubuntu, connected to the internet wirelessly via a 3G phone acting as a portable hotspot
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If both Emulator and Guest are on fast wireless or wired connections, or on the same local network, performance
should be acceptable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;firewalls-and-network-connectivity&#34;&gt;Firewalls and network connectivity&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to keep network play as responsive as possible, +F uses direct communication between the Emulator and
the Guest (commonly known as Peer-to-Peer or P2P communication). Depending on your computer and internet service
provider&amp;rsquo;s security settings, you may need to change some firewall rules so that the Emulator and Guest can reach
each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Details of how to do this will vary based on the operating system, router and ISP you are using, but you need to ensure
that your computer can receive inbound UDP network traffic on ports 7000 and 7001. If you&amp;rsquo;re already familiar with
enabling multi-player games on your computer, the process you need to follow for +F will be similar to that.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Download</title>
      <link>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/download/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 May 2016 22:31:58 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/download/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;available-packages&#34;&gt;Available packages&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://download.socialthingy.com/Plus-F.exe&#34;&gt;64-bit Windows Installer&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This is the simplest way to get up and running on a compatible Windows system.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://download.socialthingy.com/Plus-F.zip&#34;&gt;Universal Zip Package&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This download is suitable for all operating systems. You&amp;rsquo;ll need to install
a recent version of Java 8 separately, in order to run. You can download this
for free from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.java.com&#34;&gt;www.java.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://download.socialthingy.com/Plus-F.deb&#34;&gt;Debian Package&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Prebuilt package for Ubuntu and other Debian-based Linux distributions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both these packages contain images of the 48k and +2 Spectrum ROMs, which are required in order for the Emulator to
operate. These ROMs remain copyright of Amstrad, and Amstrad have kindly given their permission for the
redistribution of their copyrighted material but retain that copyright.
(Full details &lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/forum/#!msg/comp.sys.amstrad.8bit/HtpBU2Bzv_U/HhNDSU3MksAJ&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;release-notes&#34;&gt;Release Notes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can read the release notes for +F &lt;a href=&#34;http://plusf.socialthingy.com/release-notes&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;licensing&#34;&gt;Licensing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;+F is distributed under an MIT license:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MIT License&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Copyright &amp;copy; 2016 Alan Gibson&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Permission is hereby granted, free of charge, to any person obtaining a copy
of this software and associated documentation files (the &amp;ldquo;Software&amp;rdquo;), to deal
in the Software without restriction, including without limitation the rights
to use, copy, modify, merge, publish, distribute, sublicense, and/or sell
copies of the Software, and to permit persons to whom the Software is
furnished to do so, subject to the following conditions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The above copyright notice and this permission notice shall be included in all
copies or substantial portions of the Software.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;THE SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED &amp;ldquo;AS IS&amp;rdquo;, WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, EXPRESS OR
IMPLIED, INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO THE WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY,
FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE AND NONINFRINGEMENT. IN NO EVENT SHALL THE
AUTHORS OR COPYRIGHT HOLDERS BE LIABLE FOR ANY CLAIM, DAMAGES OR OTHER
LIABILITY, WHETHER IN AN ACTION OF CONTRACT, TORT OR OTHERWISE, ARISING FROM,
OUT OF OR IN CONNECTION WITH THE SOFTWARE OR THE USE OR OTHER DEALINGS IN THE
SOFTWARE.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Games</title>
      <link>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/games/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 May 2016 22:31:58 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://plusf.socialthingy.com/games/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Spectrum games are available for use in emulators in a number of file formats, the most popular ones being
Z80, TAP and TZX, all of which +F can load. TAP files are at present the most reliable, although you should be able
to use a lot of Z80 and TZX files as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most authoritative sources for Spectrum games the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.worldofspectrum.org/archive.html&#34;&gt;World of Spectrum Archive&lt;/a&gt;,
which has an extensive collection of TAP and TZX files.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t forget that the classic Spectrum games we can play today on emulators remain the result of the skills and
dedication of the programmers who developed them. While many have granted free distribution rights for their games,
others have not, and it is their right to do so. As such, please be considerate when downloading emulator files,
and refer to the information &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.worldofspectrum.org/permits&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.worldofspectrum.org/permits/publishers.html&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.worldofspectrum.org/permits/individuals.html&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;
for full details on which publishers and developers have granted free distribution rights.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>